<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The compleat bone-setter wherein the method of curing broken bones, and strains, and dislocated joynts, together with ruptures, vulgarly called broken bellyes, is fully demonstrated. Whereunto is added The perfect oculist, and The mirrour of health, treating of the pestilence, and all other diseases incident to men, women and children. Also, the acute judgement of urines. / Written originally by Friar Moulton, of the Order of St. Augustine. Now revised, Englished and enlarged by Robert Turner philomathēs.</title>
            <author>Moulton, Thomas.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1657</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 182 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 96 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A89394</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M2967</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1673_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208418</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867373</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867373</idno>
            <idno type="VID">119681</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A89394)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 119681)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 209:E1673[1], 255:E1673[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The compleat bone-setter wherein the method of curing broken bones, and strains, and dislocated joynts, together with ruptures, vulgarly called broken bellyes, is fully demonstrated. Whereunto is added The perfect oculist, and The mirrour of health, treating of the pestilence, and all other diseases incident to men, women and children. Also, the acute judgement of urines. / Written originally by Friar Moulton, of the Order of St. Augustine. Now revised, Englished and enlarged by Robert Turner philomathēs.</title>
                  <author>Moulton, Thomas.</author>
                  <author>Turner, Robert, fl. 1654-1665.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 175, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.C. for Martha Harison, at the Lamb at the east-end of Pauls.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London: :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1656. [i.e. 1657]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Philomathēs" in Greek characters on title page.</note>
                  <note>"The perfect oculist", "The mirrour of health", and "Of urines" have caption title; register and pagination are continuous.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Jan: 31".</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Medicine --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Materia medica --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Health --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:119681:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The Compleat BONE-SETTER: Wherein The Method of curing broken Bones, and Strains, and Diſlocated Joynts, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with Ruptures, vulgarly called <hi>Broken Bellyes,</hi> is fully demonſtrated.</p>
            <p>Whereunto is added <hi>The Perfect Oculiſt,</hi> and <hi>The Mirrour of Health,</hi> Treating of the Peſtilence, and all other Diſeaſes incident to Men, Women and Children.</p>
            <p>Alſo, The Acute Judgement of URINES.</p>
            <p>Written originally by <hi>Friar Monlton,</hi> of the Order of <hi>St. Auguſtine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now Reviſed, Engliſhed and Enlarged by ROBERT TURNER <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>LONDON: Printed by <hi>J. C.</hi> for <hi>Martha Hariſon,</hi> at the Lamb at the Eaſt-end of Pauls. 1656.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:119681:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:119681:2"/>
            <head>To the truly worthy, and Religious Gentlewoman, M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> ELIZABETH CRESWEL, Widow, Wife to the Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <hi>Thomas Creſwel,</hi> late of <hi>Heck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field</hi> in <hi>Hampſhire</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr> Decea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and to his Honorable Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory; <hi>Robert Turner</hi> humbly dedicates theſe his ſtudies.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> CRESVVELL,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S the Lord hath abundantly bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed you with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal <hi>graces,</hi> ſo hath he likewiſe honoured you with external <hi>bleſſings;</hi> whereby you are inſtrumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal in relieving the wants, and binding up the Wounds of
<pb facs="tcp:119681:3"/>
your poor Sick and Lame <hi>Neighbours:</hi> my experience of your affections and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours thereunto, (if I were not otherwiſe obliged) is no ſmall cauſe of this aſſay. But large courteſies require large acknowledgements, from all that would not willingly lye under the <hi>Ignominious</hi> brand of <hi>ingratitude:</hi> And many have endeavoured, and ſought by this means, to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſatisfaction for benefits received: but no ſuch <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction</hi> muſt be made of my preſent <hi>intention;</hi> that is not my <hi>end</hi> and <hi>ſcope,</hi> but only to ſhew a thankful acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement
<pb facs="tcp:119681:3"/>
for your former <hi>favours.</hi> Then that I have thus choſen you out by a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle <hi>Dedication,</hi> to be the <hi>Patroneſs</hi> of theſe my <hi>Lucu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brations,</hi> I hope you will account it but a venial tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion. If therefore you ſhall pleaſe to accept of theſe my poor preſented <hi>pains,</hi> there ſhall my Ambition <hi>Anchor.</hi> And I doubt not but your reading and practiſe of this ſmall Treatiſe, will gain you the <hi>poors Prayers,</hi> and plead my <hi>excuſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>London,</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>July</hi> 23 1656.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your humble Servant alwayes to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, <hi>Robert Turner.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:119681:4"/>
            <head>To the Readers.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His is not the firſt time that I have beſtowed my pains for the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick good, having al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready tranſlated four Treatiſes in print, and as many more are in the Preſſe, of Phyſick and Occult Philoſophy: my only aime in them all, is to learn men, <hi>(if once they would learn)</hi> to admire and glorify the great power of God, who hath commanded ſuch weak means as the <hi>Herb</hi> or <hi>Graſs</hi> of the field, that grows and flouriſhes to day, and to morrow is caſt into the Oven, to preſerve the life, and cure the infirmities that the <hi>ſin</hi> of man hath originally ſubjected himſelf and all his poſterity unto; and to ſee and contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plate the power of the great Creator in the influence of thoſe ſuperiour Bodies
<pb facs="tcp:119681:4"/>
the <hi>Stars;</hi> if they are duly obſerved, and well regarded in their operations, it is a great Book ſo full of <hi>uncontrol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lable</hi> Arguments, as are enough to ſtop the mouths of all Gainſayers, and Raylers againſt <hi>Aſtrology</hi> and the Profeſſors thereof, calling them <hi>Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zards,</hi> and the art unlawful; but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to cover their Faces with ſhame, that they are ignorant therein, and of the wonderful diſpenſations of God by them.</p>
            <p>This treatiſe indeed tends not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto only, but is chiefly compoſed and made plain in the Engliſh tongue (not to make <hi>Coblers</hi> caſt away their <hi>Laſts</hi> and <hi>Auls,</hi> and ſuch fellows, &amp; ſtraight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way turn Doctors; I would never write an Engliſh line on that account; Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do I write any thing in derogation of the honor due to the learned,) but, for the uſe of thoſe Godly Ladies and Gentlewomen, who are induſtrious for the improvement of their Talent God has given them, in helping their
<pb facs="tcp:119681:5"/>
poor ſick Neighbours; expecting the recompence of the reward of <hi>Come ye bleſſed,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>when I was ſick ye vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſited me;</hi> which Chriſt the righteous judge ſhall give them; accounting what they do for the poor members of his, as done to himſelf: and not for thoſe who think they were created for no other end, and had eſtates given them to bestow &amp; ſpend in painting their Faces, deform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themſelves with ugly black patches, minding nothing but their criſping<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pins and curling Irons, powders and perfumes; going with ſtretched-out <hi>Necks,</hi> like thoſe in <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> but never remembring the afflictions of <hi>Joſeph;</hi> not regarding the anſwer of <hi>Abraham</hi> to <hi>Dives</hi> when he cryed for a drop of water to cool his Tongue: <hi>Remember, That in thy life-time thou haſt had thy good things,</hi> &amp;c. nor fearing that dreadful ſentence of <hi>ITE MALEDICTI.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have made this plain to every Vulgar capacity; putting all the Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal
<pb facs="tcp:119681:5"/>
terms in words at length, and plain Engliſh, that ſo people who are able, may eaſily make Medicines for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and reap the harveſt of the ſown Spring</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Of <hi>Robert Turner</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>London</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>23</hi> July <hi>1656. from my ſtudy at Chriſts-Church in Carpenters-yard.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:119681:6"/>
            <head>The Contents.</head>
            <list>
               <head>A.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Aches.</hi> 100, 101.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Against infected Airs.</hi> 146, 154, 155.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>B.</head>
               <item>Broken bones. <hi>1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Bones putrified. <hi>16, 17.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To keep a broken Bone being ſet, from fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling out again. <hi>6, 7.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To ſtanch bloud. <hi>15.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Broken Bellyes. <hi>30, 31, 32, 33.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Bowells to ſtrengthen. <hi>50.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Bleared Eyes. <hi>64, 66.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Breast. <hi>123</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Spitting Bloud. <hi>126.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Stinking Breath. <hi>127.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>C.</head>
               <item>Callus to ingender. <hi>45.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Pultis for Childrens Cods that are broken. <hi>36, 37.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Clyſters. <hi>38, 49, 50, 106.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Lotions for the Cod. <hi>39.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Cods putrified. <hi>46, 47.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Confection for a Rupure. <hi>51, 52.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Clyſters for the Head-ach. <hi>106, 109.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Conſumption. <hi>123.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:119681:6"/>Dry Cough. <hi>123, 144, 145.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Tough Cough. <hi>124, 125.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Cold and Cough. <hi>128, 129, 130.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Cramp. <hi>142.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Confections againſt the Plague. <hi>154, 155.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>D.</head>
               <item>A Drink for a Rupture. <hi>57.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Drink for the Eyes. <hi>68.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Drink for the Head. <hi>105.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Decoction for the ſame. <hi>107.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Drink for the Head-ach. <hi>110.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Deafeneſs. <hi>112, 113.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>E.</head>
               <item>Waters for Eyes. <hi>53, 54, 55, 56, 57, 58, 92, 93.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sore Eyes. <hi>59. 60.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Pain in the Eyes. <hi>60, 67, 74.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Oyntment for Eyes. <hi>64, 65, 73, 80.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Pin and Web in the Eye. <hi>6<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> 71.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Blaſted Eyes. <hi>67.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Hurt or thorne in the Eye. <hi>71.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Rheumatick Eyes. <hi>73, 74.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Redneſs of the Eyes. <hi>74, 75, 76.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Hot Eyes. <hi>77.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Bliſters in the Eyes. <hi>78, 79.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Itching Eyes. <hi>80.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Spots in the Eyes. <hi>87.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Electuary for the Head. <hi>110.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Pain in the Ears. <hi>113.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:119681:7"/>Noiſe in the Ears. <hi>113, 114.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>F.</head>
               <item>Fomentations. <hi>42.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Frantick perſons to cauſe ſleep. <hi>134, 135.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Falling ſickneſs. <hi>143, 144.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>G.</head>
               <item>Guts falling into the Cod. <hi>48, 49.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Gargariſme for the Head. <hi>108, 131.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Gums impoſthumated. <hi>120, 121.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Gout. <hi>142.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>H.</head>
               <item>Head-ach. <hi>62, 99, 100, 101, 103. 104, 107.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Haw in the Eye. <hi>64.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Honey to prepare for the Eyes. <hi>89.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Hoarſeneſs. <hi>123.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Head to cleanſe. <hi>131.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To draw moiſtures out of the Head. <hi>132. 133.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>gthen the Heart. <hi>137.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>J.</head>
               <item>To ſet a Joynt. <hi>5.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Joynts luxated. <hi>20, 21.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Impoſthumes in the Head. <hi>101.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Impoſthumes in the ear. <hi>115, 116, 117.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Againſt Infection. <hi>151, 152.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>L.</head>
               <item>Lotions. <hi>39, 112.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Liver to ſtrengthen. <hi>42.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:119681:7"/>Lungs infected to help. <hi>123.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Lozenges for hot Rheumes. <hi>144.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Legges ſcabbed. <hi>146.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>M.</head>
               <item>Withered Members. <hi>25.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mirrour of Health. <hi>99.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Meagrim. <hi>101, 102.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Memory to ſtrengthen. <hi>131, 132, 133.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>N.</head>
               <item>Noiſe in the Ears. <hi>114, 115.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Bleeding at Noſe. <hi>115.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>O.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Oyntments.</hi> 10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15, 64.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The perfect Oculiſt.</hi> 53.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Oculiſts Electuary.</hi> 94, 95.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>P.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Plaiſters.</hi> 15, 18, 19, 22, 23, 42, 43.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Pultis for Ruptures.</hi> 36, 37.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Pills.</hi> 41. 107.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Purges for a Phlegmatick Rupture.</hi> 43, 44.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Plaiſter for the ſame.</hi> 44, 45.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Perle in the Eye.</hi> 68.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Powder for Eyes.</hi> 69, 70, 88, 89, 90, 92, 97.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Pomander for Eyes.</hi> 90.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Purblind.</hi> 98.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Perfume for the Head.</hi> 118.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Powder for the Head-ach.</hi> 111.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Potion for to purge the Head for a weak
<pb facs="tcp:119681:8"/>
ſight.</hi> 97.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Palſey.</hi> 135, 136, 137.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Againſt Poiſon.</hi> 137.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Dead Palſey.</hi> 138, 139. 140, 141, 142.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Pleuriſy.</hi> 145, 146.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Pain in the back.</hi> 145.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Plague.</hi> 146, 147, 148, 149, 150, 152, 156, 157, 158, 159.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Pomanders.</hi> 152, 153.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Pills againſt Peſtilence.</hi> 153, 154.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Powders for the ſame.</hi> 155.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>R.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ruptures.</hi> 26 27, 30, 31, 32, 33.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Drink for Ruptures.</hi> 35, 36.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Oyntment for Ruptures.</hi> 38.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Rheume.</hi> 144.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>S.</head>
               <item>Sprains. <hi>20, 21.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Salve for ſwelling in the Members. <hi>29, 30.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To cleer the Sight. <hi>58, 59.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Salgem. <hi>63.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Swelling of the Eyes. <hi>89.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Speech loſt to reſtore. <hi>121, 122, 123.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Speaking in ſleep. <hi>126.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sickneſs and pain in the ſide. <hi>129.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Squinancy. <hi>130.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To cauſe Sleep. <hi>134, 135.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To Comfort the Stomach. <hi>137.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:119681:8"/>
            <list>
               <head>T.</head>
               <item>Tumors. <hi>28, 29.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Tabulats for the Eyes. <hi>96.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Tooth-ach. <hi>117, 118, 119, 120.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To make Teeth white. <hi>120.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Againſt ſtinking Teeth. <hi>120.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Tumor in the Throat. <hi>130.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Trembling in the joynts. <hi>137, 138.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>U.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ulcers.</hi> 17, 18, 19.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Urine to provoke.</hi> 41, 42.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>To make the Voyce cleer.</hi> 124, 125.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of Urines.</hi> 156, 157, 158, 159, 160, &amp;c.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>W.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Windy Rupture.</hi> 38.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Watry Rupture.</hi> 40.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A Water for the ſight.</hi> 55, 56, 60, 61, 62, 63, 96.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Watry Eyes.</hi> 68, 81, 82, 83, 84, 85.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Wheezing.</hi> 124, 125.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Any of all theſe Medicines, beſides many others, as Pumicils, and a powder for to clenſe and whiten the Teeth, prevent the Tooth-ach, and faſten looſe Teeth, Lozenges for the Cough, and an excellent Cordial Water, called <hi>Aurum Potabile,</hi> effectual againſt all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections
<pb facs="tcp:119681:9"/>
agues, and ſurfets, being taken and ſwear upon, with many other Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, far exceeding the intellect of the Moderne Speculator of Spittle-fields, are prepared, and to be had at Mr. <hi>Hepburns</hi> in the Carpenters-yard in Little Brittain, by <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <closer>Δόξα τῶ Θεῶ</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:119681:9"/>
            <head>The PREFACE Sheweth the minde and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of the Author, in ſetting forth this treatiſe: which take as followeth in his own words.</head>
            <p>COnſidering that this treatiſe is very needful and neceſſary for a Common-wealth, and amongſt the Common liege-people: I <hi>Thomas Moulton</hi> Doctor of Divinity of the Order of the Fryers of St. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> am induced to Compoſe and publiſh the ſame for divers cauſes.</p>
            <p>One is <hi>Prayers</hi> of my own Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>[A thing it ſeems in thoſe dayes more eſteemed then profit.]</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Another is <hi>cauſe</hi> of prayers of many worthy Gentry.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:119681:10"/>Another is Compaſsion that I have of the <hi>poor</hi> people; who oftentimes are deſtroyed and periſh for want of help.</p>
            <p>And the fourth cauſe that moveth me hereunto is pure Conſcience, for every Chriſtian Man and Woman are bound by the Law of Conſcience, if they know their fellow-Chriſtian in pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ril, or likely to fall into any miſchief, to help them if he may, by his Counſel, with his Travel, and with his goods. And theſe four cauſes moved me to compound and gather this treatiſe, and that every man both learned and leud, rich and poor, may do thereafter, and thereby come to be their own Phyſitians in time of need; And therefore I have preſcribed Remedies for divers other diſeaſes that hurteth or grieveth the body of man: and in the firſt place, of broken bones, and luxated or diſlo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated joynts.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:119681:10"/>
            <head>The Compleat <hi>BONE-SETTER.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of broken Bones.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His is an accident of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten happening in the Country amongſt poor people, where Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geons, and eſpecially good ones, are very ſcarce, and oftentimes remote; and thereby many times enſues much dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to the party thus afflicted, through the neglect or perchance miſdreſſing of his wound: and therefore it ought dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently to be regarded.</p>
               <p>The firſt progreſſe that is to be made in the remedying of any ſuch miſchance, is diligently and dexterouſly to joyn and reunite together the fractured Bones into their proper ſeats &amp; places again; that thereby the member may
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:119681:11"/>
be again enabled to perform his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per office he is ordained for by God and Nature.</p>
               <p>Secondly, in the next place care is to be taken, that the bones thus reduced to their proper form and figure, be ſo kept and preſerved without motion, to gather ſtrength.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, to uſe means to ingender <hi>Callus,</hi> whereby the parts of the broken bones are conglutinated, joyned and faſtened together again.</p>
               <p>And fourthly, to take heed to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent and preſerve the part afflicted, from thoſe accidents which in ſuch caſes are apt to follow the fracture of the Bone, bringing much hurt to the patient.</p>
               <p>Firſt therefore, to joyne and ſet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain the broken Bones into their right and proper place; obſerve how and which way the member where the Bone is fractured, doth extend and ſtretch it ſelf: if the member where the Bone is broken, doth ſtand upwards, and is pricking, ſhewing an inequality when it is touched; it certainly mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſts, that the broken Bone is out of his natural place<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> wherefore to reduce the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:119681:11"/>
ſame again, the fractured member is decently to be extended, and that part of the Bone which is depreſſed or cruſhed down into the fleſh, to be gently lifted up; and that part which ſtandeth upwards, to be put down, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till both ends of the broken Bone do and be united and cloſed together, and brought again into their natural and proper place; having a diligent care that the member be not too immode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately extended and drawn out, for that will bring very vehement pain, and conſequently the Fever, Palſey, Convulſions, and ſuch like accidents will purſue it: and oftentimes by this means, the fibres and threads in the heads of the Muſcles be broken; whereupon lameneſs enſues.</p>
               <p>Therefore to proceed rightly, and avoyd ſuch danger, let one man lay his hand on the member above the fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctured or broken place, and another on the nether part of the member un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the fractured Bone; and ſo gently and moderately ſtretch and extend the member, till both parts of the Bone do meet together in their proper place: then form it together, till you
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:119681:12"/>
feel you have brought it again to its natural form and figure, and the Bone be repoſed in his due place; Which being done, then, and not till then, ſhall the Patient be eaſed of his pain.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To keep the Bone, being ſet, that it fall not out again.</head>
               <p>THE ſecond progreſſion to be made in the effecting this Cure, is to keep the fractured Bones, being reduced and brought to their proper place and figure, that they ſtart not out again.</p>
               <p>The means to be uſed in the effecting hereof, is to uſe apt and con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>enient ſplinting, binding, ligature, and rolling of the fracture; and by all means to keep the member without motion, as much as poſſible may be.</p>
               <p>But when you have reduced the member, or to ſpeak more plain, ſet the broken Bone, before you roll up the member, mix ſome Oil of Roſes, and the white of an Egge together, and dip therein a ſoft linen cloth, and lay it all over the place, that it may compaſſe
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:119681:12"/>
it all about, and above and below it; and then roll up the member, but not too hard, ſo as to compreſſe it, &amp; draw humors, cauſing inflammation therein; nor ſo ſlack, that the broken Bones ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate again: but alwayes remember that in meaſure reſteth virtue.</p>
               <p>Begin your roller ſmoothly upon the broken place, going three or four times about it, untill you have compaſſed about the ſound place above and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low it.</p>
               <p>Wet your rollers well in Water and Wine, before you uſe them; and if the place be much afflicted with any Vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment pain or inflammation, then the member ought to be wrapped about with fine Wooll, or towe well carded, and wet in Oxicratum, or Oil of Roſes.</p>
               <p>Then, to defend the member from accidents, and to keep it together, and ſtrengthen the ſame, lay upon the rol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers a plaiſter or Cerecloth, made of Wax melted in Oil of Roſes; but if there be beſides the broken Bone any bruiſe or hurt in the fleſh, then do not apply any Oil or Cerecloth to it; but in ſtead thereof, Cloths dipt in red and Stiptick Wine.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:119681:13"/>Alſo, to keep the member from pain and accidents, there muſt be ſplints prepared, to put about the broken member; which ſplints muſt be ſmooth and equal, without ruggedneſs or crookedneſs, and are to be thus ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed: Firſt, wet cloths in Roſe-water, and then lay them upon the Roller three or four times double; then roll Wool or Cotton round about the ſplints, and place them about the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, about the bredth of a finger one from another; and bind them gently on, taking heed that you do not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe the member, nor touch any joynt, if the broken Bone be neer a joynt, leſt the joynt do thereby be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come inflamed and ulcerate: but make your ſplints the ſhorter and ſmaller, if the fracture be neer to any joynt.</p>
               <p>Now after this progreſſe, if the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient receive eaſe, &amp; no pain, inflamma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or itching be fell in the fractured part; then let the ſplints remain on and unopened twelve or fifteen dayes: but if on the contrary, any of the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned accidents happen, then you muſt unrole the Member the third day at the furtheſt, and foment and waſh
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:119681:13"/>
the place with warm water, to put away the pain and itching.</p>
               <p>It is likewiſe good to prevent and remove ſuch accidents as uſually at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend theſe miſchances; as gangrenes, ulcers, inflammation, itchings cauſed through immoderate dryneſs or moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture, and for the moſt part extream pain; which the Patient will quickly be too ſenſible of then muſt you ſpeedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly looſe the binding about the broken place, and take off your roller; which being done, foment and bathe the place with Oil of Roſes, Vinegar, before and hereafter mentioned; and alſo uſe <hi>Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guentum Album,</hi> and <hi>Unguentum Popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leon,</hi> or either; and do not either roll or ſplint up the Member again, till the pain abateth, and the inflammation cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, but only endeavour to ſtrengthen and keep the Member together, and afterwards roll it, and ſplinter it as before: and to ſtrengthen the weakned Member, this following is very good.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:119681:14"/>
               <head>A ſpecial Oyntment to reſiſt accidents, and ſtrengthen a broken Member.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>TAke Camomile,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mallows,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Balme and the Rootes thereof, of each one handful,</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Chop and ſtamp them very ſmall, and then take May-Butter 2 pound, Doggs Greaſe 1 pound and a half, and therein boyl the Herbs very well: ſtrain it, and then
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Take Wax five ounces and a half,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Ammoniacum,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Galbanum, of each</hi> 2 <hi>ounces.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Diſſolve the Gum in Vinegar, and ſtrain it; and then boyl it till the Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar be waſted away: then, melt the Wax amongſt it; then put amongſt the ſtrain'd Herbs before, and when it is almoſt cold
<list>
                     <pb n="11" facs="tcp:119681:14"/>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Take Bevercod</hi> 1 <hi>ounce and a half,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Oil of Camomile</hi> 2 <hi>ounces and a half,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Oil of Bayes</hi> 16 <hi>ounces.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Mix all this together into an Oynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and reſerve it as a ſpecial ſecret for your uſe: And when you have oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to uſe it, melt a little of it, and therewith anoynt the grieved place, and afterwards apply thereon this Cerecloth following.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Cerecloth for broken Bones.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Take Frankincenſe,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Galbanum, of each</hi> 3 <hi>quarters of an ounce,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Maſtick</hi> 1 <hi>ounce,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Wax</hi> 3 <hi>ounces,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Roſin</hi> 1 <hi>ounce and a half,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Oil an ounce:</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Diſſolve the Galbanum in a little Vinegar, and then melt all together in the Oil; and afterwards ſtrain it through a Cloth, and then dip your Cerecloth therein, and apply it after the anoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:119681:15"/>
               <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Take Sallat-Oil</hi> 4 <hi>ounces,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Wax half an ounce,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Maſtick half an ounce.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Beat the Maſtick to powder, and melt the Wax in the Oil; and when it is almoſt cold, put in the Maſtick, and temper them well together, and uſe it as before is directed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For the ſame.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Take Virgins-Wax,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Frankincenſe, of each half an ounce,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Linſeed Oil</hi> 4 <hi>ounces.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Melt and incorporate them all well together, and dip a Cerecloth therein, and uſe it as the other.</p>
               <p>Alſo for the ſame, becauſe if you have not one Medicine in readineſs, I preſcribe many, that you may ſpeedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly apply what remedy is next at hand:</p>
               <p>Take Wax and freſh Butter, and melt them together, and apply it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:119681:15"/>
               <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
               <p>Take Fenegreek meal as much as you think good, and Comphrey; pound the Comphrey ſmall, and boyl them together in Water, till they be as thick as grout, and apply it moderately warm to the fractured place.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For the ſame.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Take Litharge of Gold,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Bolus,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Comphrey, of each</hi> 3 <hi>ounces,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Bean-meal, one ounce and a half:</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Beat them all together, and infuſe them in good Vinegar one night: then
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Take Wax,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Roſin, of each</hi> 3 <hi>ounces,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Sallad-Oil</hi> 12 <hi>ounces.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Incorporate them all well together on the fire, and let them boyl till all the Vinegar be conſumed. Then when it is almoſt cold, ſtir into it two ounces of Dragagant in powder, that hath
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:119681:16"/>
been well ſteeped in Wine, and ſo make it into a plaiſter, and apply it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another very good for the ſame, and for other Ruptures.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Take Saffron,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Euphorbium,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Long pepper; of each</hi> 1 <hi>Dram.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Roſin five ounces,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Aquavitae,</hi> 1 <hi>ounce and a half.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Diſſolve the Roſin in Aquavitae, and beat all the reſt to powder, and then boyl them all together till the Aqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitae be conſumed; and afterwards add to it as much Wax as is ſufficient to make it into a plaiſter, and reſerve it for the uſe aforeſaid.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another plaiſter for the ſame.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Take Ammoniacum half an ounce,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Galbanum</hi> 3 <hi>quarters of an ounce,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Wax,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Turpentine; of each</hi> 4 <hi>ounces,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Myrrhe a quarter of an ounce.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Diſſolve the Gums in Wine, and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:119681:16"/>
then melt them all together; and when it is almoſt cold, put in the Myrrhe, and make thereof a plaiſter for your uſe.</p>
               <p>But if together with the breaking of the Bone, there happen any wound or flux of blood, then indeavour to ſtanch the blood: for which you may uſe this powder following.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Powder to ſtanch blood in a wound.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Take of Frankincenſe,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Arſenick,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Aluminis Succarini; of each two ounces.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Calcis Vivi</hi> 6 <hi>ounces.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Mix them all together into fine pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and add thereto a pinte of Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, and boyl them together till the Vinegar be conſumed; then let it dry in the Sun, or againſt the fire, and make it again into fine powder; then to 3 ounces of this powder, add half an ounce of Bole-Armoniack, and one ounce of Pulvis Alcamiſtinis, and mix them all together into a very fine pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and reſerve it for your uſe, to ſtanch any flux of blood in a wound.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:119681:17"/>
And when you have any occaſion to uſe it, take 4 ounces of this powder, and incorporate it with whites of Egges; then take a bolſter of towe, bigge enough to cover the place where the wound is, and dip the towe in Vinegar, and preſs it out again; then ſpread your Medicine on the towe, and after ſtrowe a little of the dry powder upon it, and apply it; and after lay upon this many more little bolſters of towe, as much as is needfull to ſtanch the blood. And proceed in the cure, as you do in the cure of green wounds, if there be no Ulcer, or inflammation, or putrifaction in the Bones; but if the Bones ulcerate or putrify, then to reſiſt the ſame, uſe theſe Medicines fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For putrifaction of the Bones.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Take burnt Lead</hi> 2 <hi>ounces,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Myrrhe half an ounce,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Aloes,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Opopanacum,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Iron Droſſe,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Burnt Squinant,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Rindes of firre-Tree; of each <hi>1</hi> dram.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:119681:17"/>Make them all to a powder, and ſtrew thereof upon the putrified Bone; it ſeparates the putrifaction, and heals the place very much.</p>
               <p>Alſo waſh the place with water, wherein Sal Armoniak hath been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cocted.</p>
               <p>If there be any ulcer therewith, then have a care you uſe no Oil thereunto, for Oiles bring putrifaction in Ulcers; but waſh the Ulcer with this Medicine following.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For Ulcers in broken Bones.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Take White-wine</hi> 4 <hi>ounces,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Roſe-Water two ounces,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Burnt Allom</hi> 1 <hi>quarter of an oun.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Verdigreaſe</hi> 1 <hi>dram,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The White of an Egge ſodden hard.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Bruiſe the white of the Egge ſmall, &amp; boyl them all together a little gent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; then ſtrain it, and keep it well ſtopt for your uſe; and afterwards if it be too thick or too ſtrong, add ſome more Wine and Roſe-Water unto it, and uſe it as before is directed: And after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards lay upon the ſore this plaiſter following.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:119681:18"/>
               <head>A Plaiſter for Ulcers.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Take Oil of Roſes</hi> 3 <hi>drams,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Oil of Camomile</hi> 1 <hi>dram,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Ceruſe</hi> 1 <hi>quarter of an ounce,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Dragons blood,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Bolus; of each half an ounce,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Camphire</hi> 1 <hi>dram,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Litharge of gold half a dram,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Tutty prepared a quarter of an ounce,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Coral</hi> 1 <hi>dram.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Make them all into a plaiſter with Wax, as much as is ſufficient; ſpread it on leather, and lay it upon the Ulcer.</p>
               <p>But if theſe accidents happen not, or at leaſt be removed; then endeavour to ſtrengthen and Conglutinate the fractured Bones; which is done by a certain Nutriment or ſubſtance that groweth out of the Bones, which gleweth them, and cauſeth to Unite and grow together. This nouriſhment is called <hi>Callus,</hi> which muſt be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed by all means. When once it begins to grow, you ſhall perceive it by theſe ſigns; the inflammation ceaſeth,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:119681:18"/>
and the pain is abated, and the member again reduced to it's natural Colour. To ingender <hi>Callus,</hi> let the patient uſe meats that are groſſe and viſcous, and breed good juyce: and that the <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus</hi> may be ingendred neither too big nor too ſmall, have reſpect to the dyet, fomentation and plaiſters. If the <hi>Callus</hi> grow but ſlowly, that there be need to increaſe it, uſe plaiſters that do moderately heal; of which ſort here be many directed, in this book. And on the contrary, if it appear too big, uſe Aſtringent Medicines, a compreſſing ligature or binding; apply alſo a plate of lead upon the place, And uſe fomen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations made with Oil, Salt-Peter, or Water and Salt made hot. But if the member appear ſmaller and leaner then ordinarily and naturally it was before, then apply unto the affected member hot attractive Medicines. Let the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient uſe large dyet, and voyd all things cauſing Melancholy.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:119681:19"/>
               <head>Of eluxation of the joynts, and to ſet a Bone put out of joynt.</head>
               <p>THE Greeks call this <hi>Exarthrema,</hi> the Latines <hi>Eluxatio;</hi> which is as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as to ſay, a Joynt writhen or ſtarted aſide out of its natural place in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to another; ſo that the free natural mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof is thereby hindred: ſo that if the Bone be quite out of joynt, then this is called an eluxation; or a luxation only, without a compound, you may call it, if you pleaſe; but if it be only a little extorted and ſtrained aſide, that is not properly a luxation, but only a ſtrain or wrench. If the joynt be luxated, then muſt manual operation be uſed to ſet the ſame, and reduce it to its proper place; which is the firſt intention to be uſed in this caſe. And the manner of this opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion muſt be in this manner: to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the bone out of his ſocket into his natural ſeat, extend the member de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cently and tenderly with the hands, till you feel the Bone brought again into his proper place; but ſometimes the operation of the hands ſufficeth, not to
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:119681:19"/>
perform this work alone, but inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and bands prepared fit for that purpoſe muſt be uſed, as <hi>Hippocrates</hi> teacheth, <hi>Hippocrates lib. de Luxatis &amp; fractis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Luxated member being well reduced again to his natural place, your next intention muſt be to endeavour to ſtrengthen and confirm the affected joynt, and keep the Bone that it ſlip not out of its place again; for which purpoſe, have Rollets and Splints in readineſs to bind up the member, and keep it from hurt and motion. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you roll or bind up the ſame, anoint it with Oil of Roſes, and lay upon it ſome old fine Linen-cloths wet in Oil of Roſes, or whites of Egges, and apply them to the joynt; then gently roll up the member, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving firſt wet your Rollers in Water and Vinegar mixed together; then ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply your ſplints about the joynt, if there be neceſſity: and they may be made of leather or paſtboard.</p>
               <p>This being done, if the patient be at eaſe, and no accidents happen, open it not again in ten dayes: if any inflam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation happen, ſome refrigerating
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:119681:20"/>
Cerecloth is good to be uſed. And to prevent and ſtop defluxions of humors, which may chance to fall down and weaken the joynt, this plaiſter follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is very good to withſtand the ſame.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Take Colophonia,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Pitch; of each</hi> 1 <hi>ounce,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Galbanum,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Myrrhe,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Ammoniacum,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Frankincenſe; of each</hi> 3 <hi>drams,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The Muſcilage of Holly-hocks</hi> 3 <hi>quarters of an ounce,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Polypody Roots,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Miſleden,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Heartwort; of each</hi> 1 <hi>quarter of an ounce,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Wax</hi> 1 <hi>ounce,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Turpentine</hi> 3 <hi>quarters of an ounce.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Diſſolve the Gums in Vinegar, and then put to it the Wax, Pitch and Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentine: melt them together, and boyl them over a gentle fire, till the Muſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage and Vinegar be conſumed; then temper the other things being beaten
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:119681:20"/>
very ſmall, amongſt them, and then make it into a plaiſter.</p>
               <p>Spread of this Plaiſter upon a cloth or peece of leather, and lay it on the grieved place.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another Plaiſter for the ſame.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Take Holly-hock Roots</hi> 3 <hi>ounces,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Acorn-budds</hi> 3 <hi>quarters of an ounce.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Flowers of Self-heal</hi> 1 <hi>ounce and a half,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Sallet-Oil,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Oil of Mirtles; of each</hi> 3 <hi>quarters of an ounce,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Red Wine</hi> 24 <hi>ounces,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Self-heal Water</hi> 12 <hi>ounces;</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Frankincenſe,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Myrrhe; of each</hi> 1 <hi>dram,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Deeres ſuet</hi> 1 <hi>ſcruple and a half,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Turpentine half an ounce,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Sealed earth half a dram,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mumy two Drams and a half.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Firſt bruiſe the Holly-hock roots, Self-heal flowers, and Acorn-budds, very ſmall, and beat them to pap; then add thereunto the Wines, Oils, and Self-heal Water, and boyl all toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:119681:21"/>
till the Wine and Water be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed; then ſtrain it out hard, and put in the Frankincenſe, Myrrhe, Deeres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuet and Turpentine; then ſeeth them again, till the moiſture be conſumed; then put in the Sealed-earth and Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, and as much Wax as is ſufficient to make it into a Plaiſter: which is very good for all Luxations and broken Bones, to aſſwage the pain, and ſtrengthen the ſinewes.</p>
               <p>In all ſuch accidents, as broken and diſlocated Bones and joynts, have a care to defend the afflicted Member from inflammation and humours that are apt to flow thereunto; To prevent which, a moderate dyet muſt neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily be uſed, and that not only in this, but in all other diſtempers; for health conſiſts in mediocrity: and alſo, if need require, purging and letting blood are not amiſſe to be uſed.</p>
               <p>It will not be here amiſſe, to add ſome remedies fit to be uſed for the ſhrinking of ſinewes, and withered joynts, and contractures, which often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times happen after Luxation of the joynts, or fractures of the Bones; which many times happens after ſuch
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:119681:21"/>
miſchances, if the ſame be long before they be cured.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Salve very good for an extenuated or withered Member.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Take Cats Greaſe,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Deers-ſuet,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Bears-Greaſe,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Hogges-Greaſe,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The marrow of Neats feet,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Honey,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Doggs-Greaſe,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Badgers-Greaſe; of each a like quantity:</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Boyl them all together in Wine to an oyntment; then ſtrain it, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with anoynt the place affected, before the fire, twice a day.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another for the ſame purpoſe.</head>
               <p>Take Sage, Mallowes, Nettles, and their Roots, Camomile, Sprigges of Juniper, of each one handful; Dogs-Greaſe, and freſh Butter, of each 3 ounces; Chop the Herbs ſmall, and boyl them to a grout, and then
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:119681:22"/>
ſtrain them through a Courſe-cloth, then put the Greaſe and Butter to it, and ſeeth it again to an oyntment; then reſerve it for the uſes before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned.</p>
               <p>And thus have we done with the firſt part of Luxated, diſlocated, and broken Bones, and withered mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, and ſhrinking ſinews: next fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows an accident many both old and young languiſh under; namely, Rup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, or broken Bellyes.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <head>Of Ruptures.</head>
            <p>THIS Diſeaſe is generally called in Latine <hi>Hernia;</hi> although there be ſeveral cauſes, degrees, and diſtinctions thereof: but generally is that which fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth down into the Cod.</p>
            <p>There is a kinde of Rupture that cometh about the Navel, or privy parts, both of Man and Woman; the Rupture of the Navel ſwelleth and hangeth out of the forepart of the Belly: for a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy whereof, theſe following Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines are convenient:</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:119681:22"/>Take Comphrey well ſtamped 1 ounce, then melt half an ounce of Wax, then mix them well together in the form of a Plaiſter, and lay it on the Navel.</p>
            <p>But if the Rupture be great, then anoynt the back-bone of the party with Bears-Greaſe.</p>
            <p>The Herb <hi>Perfoliata,</hi> in Engliſh called <hi>Thorough Wax,</hi> is very profitable for all Ruptures, either in Children or other people, if the Herb and Seed thereof be ſod, and laid upon the Rupture.</p>
            <p>A dragm of the Decoction thereof in Water or Wine given to drink, is good, or the Herb and Seed ſtamped, and the weight of a ſcruple and a half thereof given to a Child in Pap.</p>
            <p>The groyn and privy places be like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſubject to tumors and ſwellings, with heat, hardneſs; and by reaſon of the tenderneſs and ſenſibility of thoſe parts, afflicted with great anguiſh and pain: for which it is not beſides the purpoſe, to preſcribe theſe following Remedies.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:119681:23"/>
               <head>For a Tumor or ſmelling in the groyn or privy parts.</head>
               <p>TAke Muſcilage of Elecampane Roots, Linſeed, Figges, and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beſtes, of each ſix ounces, and as much Oil of ſweet Almonds, Litharge of gold prepared, three ounces; ſeeth it untill the Muſcilage be conſumed, alwayes ſtirring it: then put thereto an ounce of Wax; make it into a Plaiſter, and lay it on the place grieved.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Salve for the ſame.</head>
               <p>Take Roſin and Wax, of each 1 ounc. a great Onion, and two Lilly-Roots; ſtamp them, and ſeeth them in Goats Milk; then ſtrain them through a linen Cloth, and let it ſeeth well again; then ſtir it about until it be cold, and ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve it for the uſe aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>If there be any open Ulcer, then uſe this following.
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Take Tutty prepared</hi> 1 <hi>ounce.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Maſtick,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Frankincenſe, of each</hi> 1 <hi>quarter of an ounce,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>White Wax, half an ounce.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:119681:23"/>
Oile of Roſes a ſufficient quantity, to make it into a Salve. If the place be raw, and in great anguiſh, then anoynt the ſame with Oil of ſweet Almonds.</p>
               <p>Alſo take Argal, and put it into a new pot, and burn it till it be black; then beat it ſmall, and ſtrew it on the ſore.</p>
               <p>Theſe are only for outward ſwellings and Ulcers: if there be any inward ſore or Ulceration in the conduit of the yard, ſtoppage or inflammation, then uſe this injection following, ſpouting it in gently with a Syrringe.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Take White-Wine one pinte,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Burnt Allom</hi> 2 <hi>dragms and a half,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Verdigreaſe</hi> 1 <hi>dragm and a half.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Boyl them well together, then ſtrain it through a Cloth, and inject it with a Syrringe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Salve for the ſame, to anoynt the whole member.</head>
               <p>Take the Juice of Taſſels of Planten, and Comphrey, of each two ounces; Camphire 4; Starch and Ceruſe of each one ounce, Litharge of Gold half an
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:119681:24"/>
ounce, Tutty prepared with Roſe-water 1 dragm and a half; the whites of three Egges well beaten: bruiſe the Champhire very ſmall, then incorpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate them all together in a leaden Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and make a Salve thereof, for the uſe aforementioned.</p>
               <p>But to return to ſpeak of the Rup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures falling into the Cods: of which there are ſeveral cauſes and kinds; one is a ſwelling or puffing up of the Cods through wind; Another, and that is moſt properly called a broken belly, when the Rym of the belly is broken, and the bowels or guts fall down into the Cod little or much, ſometimes in one ſide only, and ſometimes into both. And another kind (with is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>properly called a Rupture) is a ſwelling of the Cod with water, and ſuperfluous matter of moiſture; to which Hydropi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal perſons are ſubject: And that Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe is very well known by the ſwelling of the Cods.</p>
               <p>But firſt we come to ſpeak of the <hi>Hernia,</hi> or broken belly, with hapneth above the Cod; the cauſe hereof is oftentimes in Children, crying, ſome loud-hooping-cough, or extream blow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:119681:24"/>
with wind; in older perſons as well as the former, falls, thruſts, blows, much labour, or heavy burdens.</p>
               <p>A ſpeedy remedy is neceſſary to be ſought after for this Rupture; for the older it grows, the more difficult it will be to Cure. Let the Patient be laid on his back, and put up the bowels gently again till they come into their due place; then lay thereon this Plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter following, ſpred upon a piece of Leather, and bind it hard on, and apply thereto a convenient truſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Plaiſter for one that is broken in the Belly.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>Take Pitch,</item>
                  <item>Maſtick; of each <hi>3</hi> dragmes,</item>
                  <item>Frankincenſe <hi>1</hi> quarter of an ounce,</item>
                  <item>Hypociſtis,</item>
                  <item>Sarcocolla,</item>
                  <item>Juyce of Sloes, of each <hi>1</hi> dram and a half.</item>
                  <item>Blood-ſtone,</item>
                  <item>Dragons blood,</item>
                  <item>Aloe; of each <hi>2</hi> dragmes and a half,</item>
                  <item>Birdlyme <hi>1</hi> dragm and a half,</item>
                  <item>Comphrey,</item>
                  <item>
                     <pb n="32" facs="tcp:119681:25"/>Galls,</item>
                  <item>Pomgranate Pills,</item>
                  <item>Fine Bolus; of each <hi>3</hi> dragmes,</item>
                  <item>Ariſtolochia <hi>1</hi> quarter of an ounce,</item>
                  <item>Sumach,</item>
                  <item>Pomgranate Flowers, of each <hi>1</hi> drag.</item>
                  <item>Deers ſuet <hi>2</hi> ounces,</item>
                  <item>Turpentine and Wax a quantity ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient.</item>
               </list>
               <p>
                  <hi>Diſſolve the Gums and Juyces in hot Vinegar or Wine, the reſt beat ſmall, and make thereof a Plaiſter, and apply it as before is directed.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another of the ſame.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>Take Pitch half an ounce,</item>
                  <item>White and Red Wax,</item>
                  <item>Litharge of Gold,</item>
                  <item>Ammoniacum,</item>
                  <item>Galbanum,</item>
                  <item>Mumy, of each <hi>2</hi> dragmes and a half,</item>
                  <item>Bridlyme,</item>
                  <item>Myrrhe,</item>
                  <item>Cypres Nuts,</item>
                  <item>Frankincenſe, of each one dragm,</item>
                  <item>Gypſum, or Plaiſter of a wall,</item>
                  <item>
                     <pb n="33" facs="tcp:119681:25"/>Bolus,</item>
                  <item>Aloe, of each half an ounce,</item>
                  <item>Maſtick,</item>
                  <item>Comphrey,</item>
                  <item>Daiſie Roots, of each <hi>3</hi> dragms and a half,</item>
                  <item>Turpentine <hi>1</hi> ounce,</item>
                  <item>Ariſtolochia,</item>
                  <item>Galnuts, of each <hi>1</hi> ounce,</item>
                  <item>Dragons blood <hi>1</hi> quarter of an ounce.</item>
               </list>
               <p>
                  <hi>Diſſolve the Gums in Vinegar, and melt the Pitch, Wax, and Turpentine; and beat to powder all that is to be powdered; then make them all toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther into a Plaiſter: you may increaſe or diminiſh the quantity of the Wax, as the cauſe requires.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another Plaiſter for a Rupture.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Take Cypres Nuts</hi> 2 <hi>ounces,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Myrrhe,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Cypres Roots,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Marjoram Gentle,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Galls,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Juyce of Sloes,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Frankincenſe,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Gum, of each</hi> 1 <hi>ounce.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:119681:26"/>Diſſolve the Gum in Wine, then tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per the reſt amongſt it, and make there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of a Plaiſter, and lay it upon the Rup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For the ſame.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Take Daiſy Roots and flowers,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Wild Tanſy flowers and roots,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Comphrey; of each half an ounce,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Maſtick</hi> 1 <hi>quarter of an ounce,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Pomgranate flowers,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Juyce of ſloes, of each half a dragm,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Hares Hair chopt ſmall</hi> 1 <hi>dragm,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Birdlyme</hi> 1 <hi>ounce,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Pitch</hi> 2 <hi>ounces,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Wax five dragms,</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Oil of Roſes, a ſufficient quantity to make thereof a Plaiſter, and apply it as before is directed: you need not take off the truſſe but once in 4. or 5. dayes, and then renew the Plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another excellent Plaiſter for the ſame.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Take Dragons blood half a dragm,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Myrrhe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <pb n="35" facs="tcp:119681:26"/>
                     <hi>Sarcocolla,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Opopanacum,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Brimſtone,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Amber,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Maſtick,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Comphrey, of each</hi> 2 <hi>dragmes and a half,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Myrtle Seed,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Yellow Myrobalaus, of each</hi> 2 <hi>drag.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Barke of Pine-apples,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Cypres Nuts, of each</hi> 4 <hi>ſcruples,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Dragagant</hi> 1 <hi>dragm.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Garden-Snayls</hi> 4. <hi>or</hi> 5.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Diſſolve the Gum in Vinegar, and add thereto as much fiſh-lyme diſſolve in Vinegar, as is ſufficient to make the reſt into a Plaiſter; mix them all together, and dry away the moiſture by a ſmall fire.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Drinke to be uſed after this Plaiſter.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Take Comphrey,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Tormentil, of each</hi> 1 <hi>quarter of an ounce,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Codwort,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Sengreen,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Cinquefoil,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <pb n="36" facs="tcp:119681:27"/>
                     <hi>Mugwort,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Herb Trinity, of each</hi> 2 <hi>handfulls,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Gariofilata,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Verbaſcum,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Broad planten, of each</hi> 2 <hi>dragms and a half;</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Roſes,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Horſe-tail, of each half a handful:</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Cut and bruiſe the Herbs groſſe, and put to them Aquavitae, and red ſeething Wine, of each ſix ounces, or ſo much as will cover it: let it ſo ſtand 14 hours; afterwards ſtrain it through, and wring it out, and ſweeten it with Syrupe of Myrtles; And give hereof from one ounce to three, according to the ſtrength of the Patient, about 6 hours after the applying of the Plaiſter laſt before mentioned.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Pultiſs for young Children.</head>
               <p>Take meal of Lupins, and burnt Linnen, of each a like quantity; and make a Pap or Pultiſs thereof with Wine, and ſpread it between two fine Cloaths, and lay it upon the Rupture.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:119681:27"/>
               <head>A milde Plaiſter for Children.</head>
               <p>Take Beans what quantity you pleaſe, ſteep them in warm water, peel them, and let them dry again; then beat them to powder, &amp; take 2 ounces thereof, Oaken-wood filed ſmal 1 oun. Comphrey ſodden in Wine, and then beat to Pap 3 ounces: Let all theſe be boyled together till it be thick; then ſpread it on a Cloth, and lay it on the Rupture, changing it three times a day, and once in the night: faſten it well on with a truſſe; continue it 4. or 5. Weeks together, till the Rupture be cured, and the Skin grown ſtrong.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Drink for a Rupture.</head>
               <p>Take Sengreen, Conſolida, Saraceni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca, red Beets, Herb Bennet, Fennel, Knot-graſs, and Pauls Betony; of each one handful: boyl them all in Wine, and drink of it twice a day, morning and in the afternoon, but not at night: let a Child continue taking it 6 Weeks, and an old body 12 Weeks.</p>
               <p>Shepherds purſe, Sanacle, and Vale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:119681:28"/>
and Harts-tongue, decocted in Wine, and drunken, are very good.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>An Oyntment for a Rupture.</head>
               <p>Take Womans Milk 16 ounces, Badgers-greaſe, Capons-greaſe, Deers-ſuet and Comphrey, of each two ounces, the innermoſt rynde of a Cherry-tree, cut ſmall, one ounce and a half; boyl them all a little together, and ſtrain it hard through a Cloth, and therewith anoynt the Rupture morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and evening.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of a Rupture through Wind.</head>
               <p>In this caſe, the Patient muſt eſchew all ſuch meats and drinks as cauſe wind; as Milk, ſweet Wine, and the like; moiſt fruits, and all moiſt meats: And uſe means to expell the wind<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for which this Clyſter following is good.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Clyſter for a windy Rupture.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Take Cumin,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Annis,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Caraway,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Fennel,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <pb n="39" facs="tcp:119681:28"/>
                     <hi>Ameos, of each one dragm,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Rue one handful and a half:</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Seeth theſe together in a quart of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, till the half be conſumed: Then take 12 ounces of this decoction; Oil of Rue, and Oil of Bayes, of each one ounce and a half; Jndia-Salt, and Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gem, of each half a dragm; Sugar 1 ounce and a half; make a Clyſter there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and give it once a day: and every morning let the Patient take a dram of Mithridate, with 2 ounces of Rue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>water, 7 hours before meat: this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pels wind marvelouſly.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>An outward Loſion for the ſame.</head>
               <p>Take Sulpher vive beaten 2 ounces, Grains half an ounce, groſly beaten; ſeeth this together till the third part be ſodden away: dip a Spunge in this wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter being warm, and lay it on the Privities, renewing it 5. or 6. times a day.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:119681:29"/>
               <head>Hernia aquoſa, or the watry Rupture.</head>
               <p>This is an Hydropical watry humor in the Liver, Veynes and pores, that doth at laſt fall down into the Cods, and is known by the ſwelling of the Cods and Navel: for a Remedy hereof, the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient muſt be purged, and keep an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly dyet; that thereby the water may be expelled out of the body: to purge thoſe humours, take this Drink following:</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Drink to purge for the watry Rupture.</head>
               <p>Take Agarit and Hermodactyls of each one dragme and a half, Ginger one ſcruple, Ireos a dragme; Hony-Water 4 ounces: then make the Hony-Water warm, and ſteep the other things there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in 24 hours; ſtrain it, and drink it warm, and faſt 6. hours after it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
               <p>Take Electuarium Indium 3 dragms, burnt Copper 8 grains, Water of blew
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:119681:29"/>
flower de Luce 2 ounces: mix them all together, and drink it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Pills for the ſame.</head>
               <p>Take the Root of <hi>Laureola</hi> one ſcruple, ſteep it 5. dayes in Vinegar, Sulpher Vive 4 grains, burnt Copper 2 grains, Licoris, Annis, and Draga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant, of each 4 grains: make pills there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of with Juyce of Roſes, and take them all at once.</p>
               <p>To provoke Urine in this caſe is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite: for which, uſe theſe things following.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To move Urine.</head>
               <p>TAke red Peaſe 6 ounces, 2 Fen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel Roots: boyl them well toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and take 5 ounces of this Deco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, at a time.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For the ſame.</head>
               <p>Take Smallage-water and Melilot-water; of each 2 ounces and a half; ſweeten it with Sugar, and drink here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of a week together.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:119681:30"/>Or for the ſame, drink Broom-water about 5 ounces at a time.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To ſtrengthen the Liver, uſe this Confection.</head>
               <p>Take Trochiſcos, Diarhodon, Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies Diacynamomi; of each 1 dragme, burnt Ivory one ſcruple, 4 ounces of white Sugar: ſeeth it in Fennel-water, and make Tabulats of it, and take of theſe a quarter of an ounce before meat.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Fomentation for the Rupture.</head>
               <p>Take Seſeli, Cumin, Camomile, and Melilot, of each one ounce; ſeeth theſe together in a quart of Water, until the third part be ſpent, and therewith bathe and foment the Rupture; and then lay this Plaiſter following upon it, binding it on warm.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Plaiſter for the watery Rupture.</head>
               <p>Take Roots of blew flower de Luce, and Roots of wild Cucumers, of each 3 ounces, Peaſe-meal and beane-meal, of each 2 ounces, Oil of
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:119681:30"/>
Rue, and Juyce of Bay-leaves, of each 2 ounces: ſeeth this together to the thickneſs of a Plaiſter, and then ſpread it on a Cloth, and bind it warm upon the Rupture.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another Plaiſter for the ſame.</head>
               <p>Take Maſtick one ounce, Cypres-Nuts half an ounce, Dragagant &amp; Gum, of each one dragme: temper theſe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with Oil of Roſes unto a Plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, and ſo apply it.</p>
               <p>If the Rupture be cauſed of Phleg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matick humours, then uſe theſe Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions which follow.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Purge for a Rupture cauſed through blood or Phlegme.</head>
               <p>TAke Turbith 1 quarter of an ounce, Ginger one dragme, white Sugar 3 dragmes: temper them together; Let the Patient take a dram hereof every fourth day with Worm-wood-water, and the other mornings between them take this Potion following.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:119681:31"/>
               <head>A Drink for the ſame.</head>
               <p>Take Water of Balme, Betony, and Worm-wood, of each one ounce and a half, Sugar half an ounce, Vinegar of Squills one ounce: mix them together, and ſo drink them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Plaiſter for the ſame, to take away the Phlegmatick matter.</head>
               <p>Take Sandaracha two ounces, Sarco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colla one ounce, Aſhes of Bean-ſtraw, or Vine-ſtocks 6 ounces, Vinegar of Squills 2 ounces, Water as much as is needfull to ſeeth them all together till they come to the thickneſs of a Plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter; and lay it upon the place, binding it on warm, as before is directed.</p>
               <p>If the Rupture be fleſhy, that is, a fleſhy excreſence growing in the Cods, which may be cauſed through over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much heat and moiſture in the Cods, whereby the blood turneth into fleſh, which much weakneth and infeebleth this member; in this caſe, ſuch meats and drinks muſt be refrained, which do over-much heat or moiſten, ſuch as
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:119681:31"/>
ſweet Wines, Sugar, delicate meats, and the like; and on the contrary, the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient muſt eat ſuch meats as are cooling and drying. The Hemorrhoids in the fundament muſt be opened together with the Liver or Median Veyne, and outwardly apply theſe Plaiſters follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Plaiſter for a fleſhy Rupture.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Take Leutil,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Night-Shade,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Roſes,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Plantayn, of each</hi> 6 <hi>ounces,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Barley-meal</hi> 12 <hi>ounces.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Boyl theſe together in a ſufficient quantity of Vinegar, and thrice as much water, adding thereto 3 whites of Egges; boyl it to the thickneſs of a Plaiſter, and lay it all over the Cod, renewing it every day, 5 or 6 dayes one after another.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:119681:32"/>
               <head>Of the Melancholy blood putrifying in the Cods, which is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Buris.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THis is the falling of Melancholy blood down into the Cod, which cauſeth great ſwelling there: and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times if the Cod be full of matter and corruption, and it remain long, it putri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyeth the Stones, and ſpoileth them; therefore care is to be taken ſpeedily to purge away, and draw out the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy humours; to effect which, it is neceſſary, that the Liver-Vein be opened, and the next day afterwards, give the Patient this purging Potion, viz. <hi>Catharticum Imperiale,</hi> with Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let-Water, or Lilly-water; and take 6 or 8 dayes following after, theſe Poti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons following: Take Violet-water, Lettice-water, and Hop-water; of each one ounce, Syrrup of Cytron-Pills one ounce and a half; drink it warm in the morning: And outwardly to aſſwage the ſwelling, take theſe Medicines fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <list>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:119681:32"/>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Take Bean-meal</hi> 3 <hi>ounces,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Muſcilage of Holly-hocks,</item>
                  <item>Camomile,</item>
                  <item>Annis Seeds,</item>
                  <item>Fenegreek Seed,</item>
                  <item>Raiſins ſtoned, of each half an ounce.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Temper them with yolks of Egges, and apply it to the grieved place.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Pultis for the ſame.</head>
               <p>Take Cow-dung, Crums of Rye-bread, Cumin, Night-ſhade, Bean-meal, Melilot, Camomile, and Oil of Lillies: pound and ſeeth them all to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and lay them on the place grieved.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For the ſame.</head>
               <p>Take Bean-meal, Lilley-Roots, Colewort-Leaves, Figges and Fene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greek-meal, of each a like quantity, and ſeeth them together being bruiſed into the form of a Pultis, and ſo ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:119681:33"/>
               <head>Of the falling of the Bowels or Guts into the Cod.</head>
               <p>THE firſt thing in this caſe, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is generally directed, is dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently to endeavour the putting up of the Bowels again into their due place; by taking hold of the lower part of the Cods, &amp; gently thruſting them up; the Patient lying on his back with his but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tocks ſomthing higher then the other part of his Body, that thereby the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wels may the eaſier be reduced to their due place.</p>
               <p>Then foment and bath the whole Cods and parts about it, with ſuch Lotions as before are directed; then lay this Plaiſter following thereupon, and bind it on with a good Truſſe.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Take Cypres-Roots</hi> 2 <hi>ounces,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mil-dust</hi> 3 <hi>ounces,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Comphrey-Roots,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Daiſy-Rootes, of each</hi> 1 <hi>ounce,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Iſinglas</hi> 1 <hi>ounce and a half,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Dragagant,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Gum,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mumey,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Burnt Ivory, of each half an ounce,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <pb n="49" facs="tcp:119681:33"/>
                     <hi>Dragons blood,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Sagapenum,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Sealed-earth,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Fine Bolus, of each</hi> 5 <hi>dragmes.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Pound the Roots, and ſeeth them with the meal in 2 parts of Water, and 1 part of red Vinegar, until it be thick enough; then mix molten Wax a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt it, as much as is needful; ſtir it well together with diſſolved Gum, till it be cold; ſo ſpread it, and apply it as before is directed.</p>
               <p>To aſſwage the pain of the falling down of the Bowels, Clyſters are very commodious to be uſed; for which, theſe following are very good.</p>
               <p>Take white Seſamum Seeds groſly beaten, Linſeed and Fenegreek; make a decoction thereof, and mix therewith Butter and Oil of Violets, and admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter it warm.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For the ſame.</head>
               <p>Take broth made of a Hen or Cock,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:119681:34"/>
and Oil of Seſamum; of each 6 ounces, Salgem half an ounce: temper them to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether for a Clyſter.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another.</head>
               <p>Take ſweet Wine 12 ounces, freſh butter, and Oil of ſweet Almonds, of each 2 ounces, Benedicta Lax, half an ounce: temper them all together for a Clyſter.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To ſtrengthen the broken place where the Bowels come through.</head>
               <p>Take Iron Droſſe ſodden in Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, and Myrrhe, of each half an ounce, Dragons blood, fine Bolus, Frankin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe, Maſtick, Sealed Earth, and Juyce of Sloes, of each one quarter of an ounce, Cypres Nuts, and Mumey, of each 3 quarters of an ounce, Iſinglas 2 ounces: make them all together into a Salve, with Wax and Roſin as much as is needful; with this anoynt the Cods thrice a day, and knit it up alwayes with a Truſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:119681:34"/>
               <head>A good Drink for a Rupture.</head>
               <p>Take Roſemary half an ounce, Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namon half a dragme, Balme-Flowers, Ginger, Borage, Nutmegs, of each half a dragme; ſeeth theſe together in 7 quarts of Water till the 4 part be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed, then add thereto 16 ounces of Honey, then boyl it again, till the third part be conſumed, and uſe it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Confection for the ſame.</head>
               <p>Take Frankincenſe, Maſtick, Juyce of Sloes, Hypociſtis, of each 1 dragme and a half, Roſes, burnt Ivory, parched Cummin, Dill-Seed, of each one drag. Cypres Nuts half an ounce, Steel filed ſmall, Iron Droſſe decocted together in red Vinegar, of each one quarter of an ounce; dryed Seeds of Pomgranates one ounce: beat them all ſmall toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; then take Honey of Roſes 18 ounces, white Sugar 12 ounces, Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nado Wine 6 ounces, Dragagant-Gum, of each half an ounce: ſeeth both of theſe Gums with Honey, Sugar, and this Juyce, till it be thick: when it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginneth
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:119681:35"/>
to be cold, put it into a Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and temper the other things a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt it, ſtirring it well together: give the Patient 2 dragmes thereof in the morning, and let him faſt 2 hours after it; and one dragme at night, 2 hours after Supper.</p>
               <p>Let the Patient keep himſelf as quiet as poſſible, forbear much ſtirring and carnal Copulation; and all exceſſe either of meat or drink; and forbear binding meat, ſtrong drink, and new Wine. So far of Ruptures.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:119681:35"/>
            <head>The perfect OCULIST.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Author firſt begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth with 6 precious Waters, profitable both for the Eyes and other things; which he thus ſets down:</p>
            <p>For to tell of 6 precious Waters, made and ſent to a Queen that ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time was in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The firſt Water is this.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Take Fennel,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Rue,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Vervaine,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Endive,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Betony,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Germander,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Red roſes,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Maydenhaire, of each</hi> 1 <hi>ounce.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Stamp them, and ſteep them in white-Wine a day and a night, and diſtil a
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:119681:36"/>
Water of them; This Water ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part in three, (<hi>that is, you ſhall draw</hi> 3 <hi>ſeveral Waters,</hi>) the firſt part ye ſhall do in a glaſſe by it ſelf: and know ye of a truth, that this Water is as pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious as Gold, The ſecond as Silver, The third part as precious as Balme; and keep theſe 3 parts in glaſſes.</p>
               <p>This Water ſhall ye give to the Rich for Gold; to mean men for Silver, and to the Poor for Balme.</p>
               <p>This Water keepeth the Eyes in cleerneſs, and avoydeth the <hi>Quitery</hi> and <hi>gounde,</hi> and cleereth and ſharpneth the ſight.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The ſecond Water.</head>
               <p>TO the ſecond Water take Salgema pound, and wrap it in a green Dock-leaf, and lay it in the fire till it be well roſted, and wax white, and put it in a glaſſe againſt the air at night, and at the morrow it ſhall be turned to white Water like unto Chryſtal; keep this VVater well in a glaſſe, and do a drop into thy Eye, and it ſhall cleanſe and ſharp thy ſight: And it is good for the evil at the heart, and for the Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phew,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:119681:36"/>
and for Sance-fleam, and for the Canker in the Mouth, and for other evills in the Body.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The third Water.</head>
               <p>THE 3 Water is as followeth: Take the Root of Parſly, Endive, <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nache,</hi> Fennel, Betony an ounce: waſh them well in Water, and bray them well, and then ſteep them well in white-Wine a day and a night, and then diſtil them.</p>
               <p>This Water is more worth then Balme: It keepeth a good ſight, and cleanſeth it of all filth; it refraineth tears, and comforteth the head, and avoideth the Water that cauſeth headach.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The fourth Water.</head>
               <p>THE 4 Water is this; Take Parſly-Seed, Annis, Caraway, Vervaine, of each 2 dragmes, Centory 10 dragmes: beat all theſe to powder, and do it in warm water a day and a night; then diſtil it. This water is a precious wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for all ſore Eyes, and very good
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:119681:37"/>
for the health of a mans body, or Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The fifth Water.</head>
               <p>THE fifth Water is ſuch, that with it you may do many marveylous things.</p>
               <p>Take <hi>Lymel</hi> of Gold, Silver, Latyn, Copper, Iron, Steel, and Lead; And take Litharge of Gold and Silver, and take Camomile and Columbyne, and ſteep all together in the Urine of a man-child a day and a night; The ſecond day in white-Wine; the third day in the Juyce of Fennel; the fourth day in the whites of Egges; the fifth day in a Womans milk that nouriſheth a man-child; the 6 day in red Wine; the 7 day in whites of Egges; and upon the eighth day, blend and mix all theſe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and diſtil a water of them, and keep this water in a veſſel of Gold or Silver. The Virtues of this water is this; it doth away all manner of ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Eyes, the Perle, the Sckome of the tears, and the<note n="*" place="margin">Tis an old En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh word; if <hi>Geofry Chaucer</hi> were here, he could tell you the meaning of it. Tis too old for me.</note> 
                  <hi>Quiters,</hi>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:119681:37"/>
and draweth again into their due form the Eye-lids that are bleared; it ſlayeth the ach of the head; And if a man drink of it, it keepeth his viſage long to be young. There is no man can tell half the Virtues of this VVater.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The ſixth Water.</head>
               <p>TAKE Lapis Caluminaris, and do it in the fire till it be red as a Roſe, and ſlack it in a pinte of white-VVine, and do ſo 9 times, and after grinde it and beat it ſmall, and ſearſe it very clean; then Infuſe it in the Sun, in Fennel-water, Vervain, Roſes, Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lendine, Rue, and three-leaved Graſſe (the diſtilled water of them, not the Herbs,) of each a like quantity, in a Vial of glaſſe, ſo that the VVater may ſettle cleer about 5 inches above the ſtone in the bottom; and when you will uſe it, ſtir it together; and take up a drop of it with a feather; and if it abide, then it is fine and good; then drop of it in an Eye that is watry or running, or an Eye that hath a dimme ſight: and for the head-ach anoynt the Temples
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:119681:38"/>
herewith; it is precious for helping the ſight, and for ache in the head.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To cleer the ſight of the Eyes, a good Water, and for itching thereof.</head>
               <p>TAKE Fennel, Roſes, Vervain, Celendine and Rue, of each 2 ounces, and diſtil water of them, which is good to clarify the ſight of the Eyes, being waſhed therewith, according to this verſe:</p>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Feniculus, Roſa, Vervens, Celedonia, Ruta,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Ex iſtis fit aqua quis lumina reddit acuta.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Of Fennel, Vervain, and the Roſe,</l>
                     <l>Herb Celendine and Rue,</l>
                     <l>A pure VVater is Compoſe,</l>
                     <l>That doth the ſight renew.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
               <p>Take red Snailes, and ſeeth them in fair water, and there will ariſe an Oyl or fat; which ſeparate clean by it ſelf, and reſerve it in a glaſſe, and
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:119681:38"/>
therewith anoynt thy Eyes morning and evening.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To Clarify the ſight of the Eyes.</head>
               <p>Take red Roſes, Smallage, Rue, Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vain, Mayden-hair, Eye-bright, En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dive, Sengreen, red Fennel, Celen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine, of each a quarter of a pound; waſh them clean, and infuſe them in white-wine a day and a night, and then diſtill them: the firſt VVater will be like Gold, the ſecond like Silver, and the third like balme. And this water is very good for all manner of ſore Eyes, for a webbe, perle, or haw.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another for ſore Eyes.</head>
               <p>TAKE Smallage, Fennel, Rue, Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vain, Egrimony, Betony, Scabious, Avens, Hounds-tongue, Eye-bright, Pimpernel, red Roſes, and Sage; Diſtil all theſe together with a little Urine of a Man-child, and five grains of Frankin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe; And of this diſtilled water, drop a drop or two into the Eyes at night when you go to bed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:119681:39"/>
               <head>For pain in the Eyes.</head>
               <p>TAKE Egrimony, Vervain, Fennel, Rue and Roſes, and put them in a Scillatory, and ſpring on them good white-VVine, and diſtil it. <hi>This water is good for ſwelling of a mans Eyes that co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth of Cold, and for bleared Eyes, and Eyes that be red with anguiſh, and eaſeth the pain of them.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another for the pain in the Eye.</head>
               <p>TAke a little Allom and powder of Mint, and mix them together; draw thereof a VVater, and put thereof a drop into the Eye, going to bed, and in the morning.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another for ſore Eyes.</head>
               <p>TAke Flowers of Hawthorn, and the Flowers of Withy, and diſtil it; make thereof a VVater, and this VVa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is good for the ſight in the Eye, and for the redneſs in the Eye, and for burning and heat in the Eye, and for Eyes that do lightly VVater; and for
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:119681:39"/>
webbs in the Eye of a Man or VVo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A good Water for the ſight.</head>
               <p>TAke Sage, Fennel, Rue, Vervain, Betony, Egrimony, Sanacle, Pim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernel, Eye-bright, Cinquefoil, and Rue, of all theſe like much, and grinde them in a Morter; then take powder of Alom, and a little Camphire, and mingle them together, and diſtil it: And know you of a truth, that this VVater is profitable for all evills of the Eyes; And reſtoreth the ſight that hath been almoſt loſt, by the ſpace of 3 years.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Water of Copporas, to make good for the Eyes.</head>
               <p>TAke Copporas, and grinde it to powder, and put a little water to it, and let it ſtand a day and a night, and ſtrain it through a Cloth. This VVater is good for the Eyes, and for the Canker in the mouth, and for <hi>noli me tangere,</hi> and to make a deer com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:119681:40"/>
               <head>Another Water for ſore Eyes, and pain in the Head.</head>
               <p>TAke red Roſes, Maydenhair, Rue, Vervain, Eye-bright, Betony, Cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mynt, of each one handful; ſteep them in white-VVine 24 hours: The ſecond day, diſtill it in a Diſtillatory. The firſt water that thou doſt diſtill, it ſhall be like colour of Gold; The ſecond, of Silver; The third, of Balme. And this is called, the precious water for Ladyes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another Water for ſore Eyes.</head>
               <p>TAke good red VVine, and Cumin, and Salt, and put it in a pot; and ſet upon the pot an Alembick, and ſtop it faſt about with good paſte, and make a ſlow fire of Cole: The firſt VVater that is diſtilled, is good for all cold ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in the Eyes of Man or VVoman; The ſecond VVater is good for all manner of hot maladies in the eyes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:119681:40"/>
               <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
               <p>Take and fill a pot of thick Dregs of good Ale, and put thereto a handful of Cumin and Salt, and put a Lembeck on thy pot, and ſtop it about with paſte, and diſtill it: a precious VVater for the Eyes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Salgem.</head>
               <p>THE VVater of Salgem is good to cleer the filth of a mans Eyes, and it is good for the ſcurffe and Morphew, and for the ſtink of the hammes and Arme-pits. Take a pound of Salgem, and wrap it up in Colewort-Leaves, and do it in the hot Aſhes, And there let it ſeeth in his own kinde, till it be turned to whiteneſs; after that, lay it on a marble-ſtone a day and a night, and that which goeth over thereof, will be a Silver Colour: Then take that, and keep it in a glaſſe, and when need is, put a drop thereof into the ſore Eye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:119681:41"/>
               <head>For the haw in the Eye.</head>
               <p>Take Pepper, and ſtamp it to powder; then take the marrow of an old Gooſes wing, and mingle it together; and do it in a Cloth, and burne it to powder, and put thereof into the Eye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For dim ſight, and bleared Eyes.</head>
               <p>Take Ginger and rub it on a whet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone, into a fair Baſon, and put thereto as much Salt, and temper it in VVine with the juyce of Eye-bright, and let it ſtand infuſing a night and a day; And then take the cleerneſs that aſcendeth above, and put in a glaſſe for uſe: and with a feather, when thou goeſt to bed, or as often as thou lyeſt down to ſleep, therewith annoynt thy eye-lyds within and without, and it will heal them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>An oyntment for ſore Eyes, approved.</head>
               <p>Take Vinegar, and put it in a clean Baſon, then take the flowers of plumbs and mingle all together, and let it ſtand
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:119681:41"/>
three dayes and three nights covered: then put it in a box, and reſerve it for your uſe, to anoynt the Eyes when need requires.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
               <p>Take Raw Cream made of Ewes milk, and ſpread it on the bottome of a fair ſcowred Baſon; then take a veſſel that hath ſtood with Ale in it 6. or 7. dayes, and pour out the Ale, and whelm the pot or veſſel over the Baſon, ſo let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it remain a whole night: then take the Cream, and keep the Cream in a box till you need it for an oyntment for ſore Eyes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
               <p>Take red Snayles that be without houſes, and ſeeth them in water; and after that, burne them on a hot tile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone to powder, and mix the powder with the fat that will ariſe above the water they are boyled in, And anoynt the Eye-lyds therewith at night going to bed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:119681:42"/>
               <head>For bleared Eyes.</head>
               <p>Take the Juyce of VVorm-wood, and mingle it with water, made of the white of an Egge; and therewith anoynt the Eyes, and it will put away the bloodineſs and aking thereof.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
               <p>Take Celendine, Rue, Planten, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis; of each a handful, and as much Fennel as of all the reſt, and ſtamp them in a new earthen pot, and let it ſtand two days and two nights, &amp; then ſtrain it, and therewith anoynt the Eyes even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and morning.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For a pin and Webbe in the Eye.</head>
               <p>Take an Egge and roſt it hard, and take the white all hot, and put in as much white Copporis as a peaſe; and while it is hot, ſtrain it through a Cloth, and let it drop into the Eye a good drop. And this for young and old is proved a good Medicine.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:119681:42"/>
               <head>For Eyes that be blaſted.</head>
               <p>Take Tutty and Calamint, and waſh them in white-Wine 9 times, and then grinde them upon a ſtone with ſome of the white-Wine, and white Gooſe-Greaſe, and Capons Greaſe; and put thereof in the eye morning and at night: approved.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For Eyes that be red, and full of pain.</head>
               <p>Take white Ginger, and rubbe it into a Baſon on a whet-ſtone, put thereto as much white Salt, and grinde them together on a Marble-ſtone; and when it is ſmall ground, add thereto white-Wine, and then temper them well to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and let it ſtand ſo a day and a night; then pour out the thinne cleer liquor that ſtandeth above, and put it in a Vyal: And when the ſick goeth to bed, anoynt well the Eyes with a clean feather. <hi>Probatum.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:119681:43"/>
               <head>For Eyes that run with Water.</head>
               <p>Take a Colewort leaf, and anoynt it with the white of an Egge beaten well, and lay it to thy Eyes when thou goeſt to bed, and let it lye all night; and it ſhall help thee by the grace of God.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To cleer the Eyes, a Drink.</head>
               <p>Take Celendine and ſtamp it, and temper it with fair water, and drink it three dayes, and it ſhall heal the head, and cleer the ſight marvelouſly.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For the Perle in the Eye at firſt.</head>
               <p>Take white Ginger that is good and fine, and rubbe it on a whet-ſtone of <hi>Norway,</hi> into a ſawcer of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ewter, and put thereto white-Wine; but let it be muddy of the Ginger, and with a fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do it into thy Eyes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:119681:43"/>
               <head>A precious Water for Eyes, called the Water of Mr. <hi>Peter</hi> of <hi>Spain.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Take Fennel, Rue, Celendine, Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vain, Eye-bright, Clary, Roſin, or the water of Roſin, and ſtamp them by the ſpace of a natural day in white-Wine, and then put all together in a Lym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beck, and diſtill a water thereof; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with waſh the Eyes: it clarifyeth and comforteth them greatly.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Powder of Maſter <hi>Peter de Villa Nova.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Take Tutty prepared one dragme, Antimony one dragme and a half, Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joram 2 dragmes, Flower of red Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral one dragme and a half, Raw Silk of the Silk-worm cut ſmall as may be, half a dragme; make hereof as ſubtil a pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der as may be made, and keep it in a box of Metal. This powder dryeth tears, and rectifieth redneſs of the Eyes: And was made for Biſhop <hi>John.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:119681:44"/>
               <head>A Powder for the Eyes, called <hi>Bonaventure.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Take a dragme of Sugar-Candy, Tutty prepared half a dragme, powder them, and waſh them with water of Roſes, and ſpread them abroad on a Baſon, and fumigate the Baſon with the fume of Lignum Aloes, and Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kincenſe; dry it, and powder it ſubtily, and keep it in a box of braſſe or pewter, And put it in the Eyes with a Pencil of Silver. This powder is good for all manner of ſpots in the Eyes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A precious Powder for a pin and Webbe in the Eye.</head>
               <p>Take two dragms of Tutty prepared, of Sandragon one dragm, of Sugar one dragme; beat them together to a very fine powder; whereof put into the Eye a little at a time: approved.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:119681:44"/>
               <head>For a hurt in the Eye, with a Thorn, Stubble, or any other thing.</head>
               <p>Take Monſear and ſtamp it, and drink the Juyce thereof; and lay three drops upon the Eye: and ſtamp Egri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, and lay it on the hinder part of the Eye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For the Webbe in the Eye.</head>
               <p>Take ground Ivy, and dreſſe the Eye with the Juyce thereof once a day, and it will deſtroy it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another for ſore Eyes.</head>
               <p>Take Centory, and make thereof an Electuary with Honey, very thick, and eat thereof. It is good for the ſtomack, and will make a man to have a good talent to his meat: And therewith anoynt the Eyes: it is very good for ſore Eyes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:119681:45"/>
               <head>A Soveraign Medicine that helpeth the ſight, and purgeth and clari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyeth the Eyes, be they never ſo bleared.</head>
               <p>Take a good quantity of Houſleek, and ſtamp it in a Morter, and wring out the Juyce clean; and put it in a broad Veſſel a day and night till it be clear, then take 20 Egges, and ſeeth them very hard; then take away the Yolk of every Egge, and ſet the ſhell hot in wheat-bran, and fill it full of the water of Houſleek; and ſo ſerve all the Egges while the water laſts, and let them ſtand ſo a day and a night, at the leaſt a day; then take the water and put it in Vials. VVith this water anoynt the Eyes morning and night.</p>
               <p>Alſo, take a Pidgeon, and let it bleed in the right Vein under the wings, and anoynt thine Eyes with the blood 9 dayes and 9 nights, and more if it be need; for this Medicine hath been proved many times.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:119681:45"/>
               <head>An excellent Oyntment for the Eyes.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Take new Hogges-lard</hi> 2 <hi>ounces,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Tutia prepared</hi> 1 <hi>ounce,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Lapis Hematis waſhed</hi> 1 <hi>ſcruple,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Aloes waſhed and powdered</hi> 12 <hi>grains,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Perles</hi> 3 <hi>grains,</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Steep the Greaſe 6 hours in Roſe-wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, then waſh it 12 times in white-Wine; powder the Tutia very fine, and make it into an oyntment with a little Fennel-water, and therewith anoynt the corner of the Eyes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For Rheumatick Eyes.</head>
               <p>Firſt, purge the Head and the Body, and let the Patient ſweat a little: Then uſe this powder following for the Eyes.</p>
               <p>Take Tutia, prepared 1 ounce and a quarter, red Coral, yellow Myrobalaus, of each 1 quarter of an ounce, Pepper half a dragme: powder them very fine, and ſtrew them in the corners of the Eyes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:119681:46"/>
               <head>A Water to waſh Rheumatick Eyes.</head>
               <p>Take Rain-water, boyl therein Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuts, Myrtle-Seeds, fine Bolus and Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pres-nuts, And therewith waſh the Eyes oftentimes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To aſſwage and drive away the pain of the Eyes.</head>
               <p>Take prepared Tutty, Camphire bruiſed very ſmall; of each one ſcruple, Roſe-water 1 ounce, white-Wine half an ounce: temper them well, and when you have occaſion to uſe it, ſtir it well about, and put a drop or two in the Eye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For redneſs in the Eyes.</head>
               <p>This oftentimes proceeds from ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluity of blood, which floweth unto the Eyes; it is neceſſary in this caſe, to apply Cupping-glaſſes to the ſhoulders, if need be, to open the Head-vein on the contrary ſide, and to purge the Body; and outwardly to apply ſuch things to the Eyes, as may repercuſſe
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:119681:46"/>
and drive back the humour offending, as followeth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For the redneſs of the Eyes.</head>
               <p>Take the white of an Egge, and bray it with Womans milk, and apply it to the Eyes; I mean, drop a drop or two thereof into the Eye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For the ſame.</head>
               <p>Take Linſeed and boyl it in water, and wet a Sponge in that Decoction; and lay it warm on the eyes; or do in like manner with the Decoction of Fenegreek or Camomile.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For the ſame.</head>
               <p>Take the Juyce of Night-ſhade, and mix it with the white of an Egge well beaten, and Oil of Roſes: make a cloth wet in it, and lay it on the Eye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For blood-ſhot Eyes.</head>
               <p>Take the Juyce of Worm-wood, bray it well with the white of an Egge, and drop thereof into the eye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:119681:47"/>
               <head>Another for pain or redneſs in the Eyes.</head>
               <p>Take broad Planten water 1 pinte, ſmall bruiſed Verdigreaſe 1 ounce, fine Bolus, Dragons blood; of each half an ounce, Camphire 1 quarter of an ounce, diſtill this in a glaſſen helm in Balneo. This water taketh away redneſs of the Eyes and pains thereof, and helpeth ſwollen Eye-lids that have long conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued; And is alſo good for all ſore mouths, and ſtinking impoſthumations therein, and eſpecial for all Ulcerations in the privy members.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For the ſame.</head>
               <p>Take water of Vervain, Eye-bright, Marjoram, of each half an ounce, Fen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel-water an ounce, Camphire half a dragme; the Gall of a great Pickerel: temper and ſtir it all together, and uſe it as the other.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>An Oyntment for red Eyes.</head>
               <p>Take Tutia half an ounce, Oil of Bay 1 quarter of an ounce, Honey and Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negar,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:119681:47"/>
of each one ſpoonful, Camphire 1 dragme; make a Salve thereof, and therewith anoynt the Eye-lids: this is alſo good for inverted Eye-lids.</p>
               <p>Nutmegs confected in Honey, do help the redneſs of the Eyes, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the ſight, being eaten.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For hot Eyes.</head>
               <p>Take water of Eye-bright, Fennel, Celandine, of each 1 ounce; Tutia pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared 3 ſcruples: Sarcocolla and Pearles prepared, of each half a dragm: temper it together, and therewith anoynt the Eyes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
               <p>Take Rue, Fennel, Vervain, of each equal parts; ſtamp them, and put to them Roſe-water and white-Wine, as much as will cover them quite over. Let it infuſe a night, and then diſtil it in a glaſſe body in balneo, and reſerve the water for the uſe aforeſaid.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:119681:48"/>
               <head>For pricking and hot Blyſters in the Eyes.</head>
               <p>This is oftentimes cauſed through over-much moiſture, ſetling it ſelf in the white or apple of the Eyes; Theſe are dangerous to be cured: The Patient muſt be let blood in the Head-Vein, and purged, to divert and carry away the humours; And firſt take for it this Medicine following.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Water for blyſtered and pricking Eyes.</head>
               <p>Take Lycium and Saffron, of each half a dragme, Juyce of ſloes 1 ſcruple; mix this with Roſe-water, and drop a little into the Eyes with the white of an Egge.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another for the ſame, to ripen and draw out the corruption, and aſſwage the pain.</head>
               <p>Take Fenegreek and Linſeed, of each one quarter of an ounce; Melilot one quarter of an ounce: ſeeth it in fair wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and waſh the Eyes oftentimes
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:119681:48"/>
therewith, and ſomtimes drop a drop thereof into the Eyes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
               <p>Take Crums of white-bread, and ſteep it in Womans milk; and lay it on the Eyes; and when it grows dry, renew it, and lay on freſh.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Confection, good for all heat, pricking and ſwelling in the Eyes.</head>
               <p>Take Eye-bright, Fennel, Cinamon, of each 3 dragms, long Pepper, Mynts, Mace, Marjoram, Vervain, Calamus, Roſemary, of each one dragme and a half, Sugar Pennets 3 ounces, white Sugar 5 ounces: with the Sugar ſeeth theſe Juyces following, of Roſes and Vervain, of each 2 dragmes, Juyce of Fennel clarifyed, five ounces, Juyce of Celendine and Rue, of each one ounce and an half; let them ſeeth almoſt as thick as a Syrrup, afterwards temper amongſt it the reſt well beaten.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:119681:49"/>
               <head>Another Oyntment, to aſſwage the pain and heat in the Eyes.</head>
               <p>Take young Endive, and ſtamp it with Oil of Roſes, or Oil of Violets, and therewith anoynt the corners of the Eyes, and Eye-lids.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Againſt itching Eyes.</head>
               <p>This commonly proceeds from a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluxion of ſalt humour, that falls down to the Eyes, and cauſeth great itching and pricking in them, which maketh the Patient alwayes very apt to rubbe them; but that he muſt by all means refrain, for that hurteth the ſight, and maketh the eyes more red, hot, and angry: he muſt be moderate in eating, and forbear ſtrong drink; purge the Body of choler, and open the Head-vein, waſh the Eyes well in Roſe-water, and afterwards foment and bath them with the Decoction of Mallows, Violet-Leaves, Vervain, and Celandine.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:119681:49"/>
               <head>For running Watry Eyes.</head>
               <p>This infirmity ſomtimes flowes from the weakneſs of the faculty retentive, And is alſo often occaſioned through ſuperfluous moiſt Rheumes, falling down from the brain upon the Eyes; and likewiſe it may be cauſed through mirth, but oftner through its oppoſite ſorrow; for that alwayes follows that kinde of deceitful pleaſure, under which exceſſive drinking ſeems to mask it ſelf: ſharpe windes, ſmoke, Coughs, ſtinking Savours, do periſh the Eyes. For help of this defluxion, uſe theſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies following.</p>
               <p>Purge the Body with <hi>Pill. Cochiae Aureae,</hi> with <hi>ſucco Roſarum,</hi> or with Pills of the 5 kindes of Mirobalaus.</p>
               <p>Forbear all moiſt ſharp meats and drinks, Salt Fiſh and Fleſh, Milk, Cheeſe, Onions, Garlick, and all that fumes into the head.</p>
               <p>Outwardly, beat the white of an Egge, and temper it with Womans milk, and drop a drop thereof into the eye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:119681:50"/>
               <head>For the ſame.</head>
               <p>Alſo take unripe Grapes, and burn the ſame to aſhes, and make it into a fine powder; and blow thereof into the Eyes, it dryeth up the Rheume, and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth away the redneſs.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another for Watery Eyes.</head>
               <p>Take Roſe-Leaves freſh half an ounc. Saffron, Spica, Indie, Gum Arabick, of each 1 quarter of an ounce: beat them ſmall, and make Cakes thereof with rain-water; And when you will uſe it, take 1 dragme thereof, and lay it to ſteep in the beaten white of an Egge, and herewith anoynt the Eyes. This repelleth the matter, and conſumeth the pain.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
               <p>Take Juyce of Fennel well clarifyed 1 ounce and a half; Aloe two dragmes and a half, a leaf of beaten Gold: mix them well together, then add to it 7. grains of Frankincenſe: diſſolve them in
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:119681:50"/>
good white-Wine, and mix them all to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with Fennel and Roſe-water; and drop of this water into the Eyes twice a day.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another for running and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moiſt Eyes.</head>
               <p>Take Myrrhe half a dragme, Blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone one dragme, Roſe-leaves one ounce: ſeeth them in a glaſſe in Balneo to the conſumption of half; then ſtrain it through a cloth, and drop thereof 4<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> times a day a drop into the Eyes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Salve for watery Eyes, to eaſe the pain, and ſtay the defluxion.</head>
               <p>Take Juyce of Rue, Oil of Mirtle; of each 2 ounces: Let it boyl untill the Juyce be ſodden away: then ſtrain it, and ſet it again upon the fire, and mix amongſt it Saphire prepared half a dragme, Jacynt one ſcruple, Antimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny one dragme, burnt Copper 1 ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, Tutia prepared 3 dragmes; let it ſeeth gently on the fire, adding there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to two or three dragmes of Wax, more or leſſe, accordingly as you deſire to
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:119681:51"/>
have it hard; when you will uſe it, melt a little, and anoynt the Eye-lids there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with.</p>
               <p>If the Rheume in the Eyes cometh of cold; then at the firſt beginning of it, take inwardly this Confection fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Confection for Watery Eyes, that come of taking cold.</head>
               <p>Take Spica Indie 5 dragmes, Agarick 1 dragme and a half, Cynamon 1 ounc. Maſtick as much as the weight of them all: make a Confection thereof with clarifyed Honey, and take thereof eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry morning.</p>
               <p>Muske and Pomanders are good for the Patient to ſmell to in this caſe, and to chew Betony in his mouth every morning.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>An outward Oyntment for the ſame.</head>
               <p>Take Bloud-ſtone prepared 1 quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of an ounce, Roſes, burnt Ivory, white and red Coral, Amber, yellow Mirobalaus, of each one dragme, Juyce of Houſleek 4 ounces: temper them to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:119681:51"/>
and ſo keep it well ſtopped; anoynt the Eye-lids every day here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, and put of the ſame a drop into the Eye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another Water for the Eyes, to dry Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarrhes and cold Rheumes.</head>
               <p>Take Gummi, the Muſcilage of Fene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greek-Seeds; of each one quarter of an ounce, of prepared Sarcocol, Spikenard, Myrrhe, Cynamon, Aloes, Bever-cod; of each half a ſcruple: powder them all together; then ſteep them in Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans milk, and drop thereof into the Eye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Salve for running Eyes, and for all Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſthumes and Pains, Scabs, Wounds, and Bloud-ſhots in the Eyes.</head>
               <p>Take Tutia prepared in Roſe-water half an ounce, freſh Hogges-greaſe one ounce, Starch 3 quarters of an ounce: bruiſe and temper them well together in a Morter, then waſh it three times in the Water of Night-ſhade, and with this anoynt the fore-head, the Temples and the Eye-lids, both within and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:119681:52"/>
               <head>A precious Water to ſtrengthen the ſight.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Take Rue,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Roſes,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Endive,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Betony,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Vervain,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Maydenhair,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Egrimony,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Clevers,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Yarrow,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Eyebright,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Pimpernel,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Sage; of each two handfuls.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Cut the Herbs ſmall, and ſteep them a day and a night in good white-Wine: then ſtrain them out, and let the Moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture run from them: then bruiſe them groſly in a Morter: then diſtil them in Balneo, and keep the water for your uſe cloſe ſtopt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For ſpots in the Eye.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Take Prepared Blood-ſtone</hi> 3 <hi>dragmes, Burne Copper a quarter of an ounce, Perles,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <pb n="87" facs="tcp:119681:52"/>
                     <hi>Red Coral, of each</hi> 1 <hi>dragm.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Gummi,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Tragacant, of each</hi> 3 <hi>dragmes,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Pepper</hi> 30 <hi>grains,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Waſhed Ceruſe</hi> 1 <hi>dragme,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Dragons blood,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Saffron,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Amber, of each half a dragme,</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Make it into the form of trochiſes of a dragme apiece; and when you have occaſion to uſe it, bruiſe one of them, and infuſe it in Womans milk, and drop a drop thereof into the Eye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another for ſpots in the Eyes.</head>
               <p>Take Frankincenſe 5 dragmes, Saffron one dragm, Ammoniacum, Sarcocolla, of each two dragmes and a half: beat them all into very fine powder, and make it into Trochiſes, with Muſcilage of Fenegreek; then when you will uſe it, bruiſe it into Womans milk, and therewith waſh the Eyes: this doth mundify and deer the ſight.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:119681:53"/>
               <head>For mists and clouds before the Eyes.</head>
               <p>It oftentimes happens in them that have the ſmall Pox, afterwards ſome clouds or white ſpots remain in the Eyes, endangering the ſight thereof; for which, take the Juyce of Corn-roſes, the Juyce of Centory; each apart or mixt together, and therewith anoynt the Eye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A powder for the ſame.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Take the dryed Juyce of Celendine 3 dragmes, Ameos one quarter of an ounce, as much white Sugar-Candy; make a fine powder thereof, and blow a little into the Eye when you go to bed.</hi> Probatum.</p>
               <p>With this Medicine, I cured my ſelf of a ſpot of whiteneſs, that grew over the ſight of my left Eye, immediately after my recovery of a grievous ſickneſs of the ſmall Pox, in October <hi>1646.</hi> by putting a little thereof into my Eye going to bed, with a piece of clean Paper, rolled in form of a quill; which in a ſhort time took the ſpot clean away, not putting the Eye to any
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:119681:53"/>
pain. <hi>Gloria Deo in excelſis.</hi> Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another Powder much commended for the ſame.</head>
               <p>Taſte Pumice-ſtones, Cuttle-bones, prepared Sarcocolla, Ariſtolochia, red Coral, Boras, of each one dragme, white Sugar-Candy 6 dragmes; make them all into a fine ſubtil powder.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Honey to be prepared for the mists be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Eyes.</head>
               <p>Take clarifyed Honey 2 ounces, the Juyce of Fennel, the Juyce of Centory, of each 1 ounce and a half; ſeeth it a little, and ſcumme it till it be cleer, and drop thereof on the cloud or white ſpot in the Eye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Plaiſter for ſwollen and extuberated Eyes, as if they would fall out.</head>
               <p>Take Shepherds Purſe, Planten, Houſleek; make a Plaiſter thereof, and apply it to the Eye: but if it proceed of weakneſs of the ſinews, then it is need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to purge the Head with Hiera, or
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:119681:54"/>
pill Cochie: uſe Gargariſmes, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with foment the mouth; and lay to the Eyes this Plaiſter.</p>
               <p>Take Juyce of Sloes, Frankincenſe, Maſtick, Cypres-Nuts, (and the Leaves of each, if you can get them,) of each a like quantity; beat them very ſmall, and mix them with the Oil of Camo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mil, and lay it on the Eyes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Pomander for to ſtrengthen and help a feeble and dim ſight.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Take Roſemary,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Nep,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Marjoram,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Penny-royal, of each</hi> 1 <hi>dragme,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Lignum Aloes,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Marjoram Gentle,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mace, of each</hi> 2 <hi>dragmes,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Muske,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Amber, of each</hi> 2 <hi>grains,</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Make thereof a powder, and bind it in a piece of red Silk, and ſmell often to it. All odoriferous Herbs, as Roſemary, Lavender, Gillo-flowers, Roſes; and all ſweet ſmelling Fruits are good for the Eyes; ſo alſo doth the ſight of
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:119681:54"/>
green Fields, green Trees, the precious ſtone Smaragdus, green Glaſſe, green Linen, ſet before the Eyes, ſtrengthen and quicken the ſight: on the contrary, lechery, and unmeaſurable Venery, Drunkenneſs, ſleeping on a full ſtomack, much reading ſmall prints or writing, vaporous Meats, moiſt Fruits, dark miſty weather, Smoke, Wind, Duſt, Idleneſs and groſſe Meat, weakens and diminiſheth the ſight.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Powder to ſtrengthen the ſight.</head>
               <p>Take Tutia prepared 10 dragmes, make it into Paſt with the Juyce of Marjoram Gentle: when it hath ſtood a night, and be well ſetled, Let it drye well; then beat it again, and add to it Ginger, long and black Pepper, and Celendine, of each 1 dragme, ſal Armoniack half a dragme, all beaten ſmall, and made Moiſt with the Juyce of Fennel; let it dry again, and ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve it: when you will uſe it, beat it into a very fine powder, and put there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of into the Eye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:119681:55"/>
               <head>A Powder to be ſtrewed upon the Head, to ſtrengthen and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the ſight.</head>
               <p>Take Cloves, Lignum-Aloes, Betony, Sandarac, burnt Ivory, Styrax, Calaminta, of each half a dragme; make them into powder, and ſtrew all the Head there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with; and when you will renew it, kemb the Head, that the firſt may come off: afterwards uſe twice a month, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you go to ſleep, one quarter of an ounce of Trochiſes of Diambra, and hold them in your mouth till they be diſſolved.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Water to preſerve and ſtrengthen the ſight, uſed by the <hi>Emperour Frederick the third.</hi>
               </head>
               <list>
                  <item>Take green Betony,</item>
                  <item>Rue,</item>
                  <item>Vervain,</item>
                  <item>Celendine,</item>
                  <item>Eye-bright,</item>
                  <item>Roſes, of each <hi>6</hi> handfulls,</item>
                  <item>Long Pepper,</item>
                  <item>
                     <pb n="93" facs="tcp:119681:55"/>Cloves, of each half a dragme,</item>
                  <item>Aloe one ounce,</item>
                  <item>Wood-bind and the flowers <hi>3</hi> hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulls.</item>
               </list>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chop all the Herbs ſmall, and diſtill it through a glaſſe body; drop of this Water into the Eyes, and anoynt the Face therewith.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another to preſerve the ſight.</head>
               <p>Take Fenegreek, Holly-hock Roots, of each 2 ounces; cleanſe them well, and boyl them in fair water by a mild fire, till half be conſumed: then ſtrain them out, and add thereto, Aloes 2 dragmes, Sugar-Candy, or Sugar of Roſes 1 ounce; ſtrain it with Roſe-water, through a Cloth, and let it ſeeth unto a Syrrup; keep it in a glaſſe cloſe ſtopt, And when you have occaſion uſe it as other Eye-waters.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
               <p>Take Roſe-water, and white Sugar-Candy, of each what quantity you pleaſe, And infuſe them in a glaſſe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:119681:56"/>
and let them ſtand in the Sun two or three dayes or more, before you uſe it.</p>
               <p>The Galls of all Ravening Birds, as alſo of partridges, of Bulls, Hares, Wolves, Foxes; and eſpecially the Gall of a Bucke, doth cleer the Eyes and ſharpen the ſight: if any one of them be decocted with Juyce of Fen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel, and clarifyed Honey, and dropt into the Eyes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Confection for a bad ſight, called Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuarium Oculiſte, or the Oculiſts Electuary.</head>
               <p>Take Silver Mountain-Seed, Eye-bright, Fennel and Cinabes, of each one dragme, Cardamome and Mace, of each one dragme and a half, Seeds of Rue and Celendine, of each one quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of an ounce; Roſemary one ounce, Annis-Seed, Lignum Aloes, Caraway, Conſolida, Saracenica, of each half an ounce: make a Confection thereof, with Sugar or Honey. This alſo ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theneth the brain, reſtoreth loſt ſight, and maketh the Spirits of the ſight ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiller and ſtronger.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:119681:56"/>
               <head>Another Confection to preſerve and ſtrengthen the ſight.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>Take dryed Betony.</item>
                  <item>Celendine,</item>
                  <item>Eye-bright,</item>
                  <item>Hyſop,</item>
                  <item>Penny Royal, of each <hi>1</hi> dragme,</item>
                  <item>Fennel,</item>
                  <item>Silver Mountain,</item>
                  <item>Coriander prepared,</item>
                  <item>Marjoram Seeds,</item>
                  <item>Baſil Seeds,</item>
                  <item>Cardamom,</item>
                  <item>Cynamon,</item>
                  <item>Ginger,</item>
                  <item>Galingale,</item>
                  <item>Nutmegs,</item>
                  <item>Cloves,</item>
                  <item>Long Pepper,</item>
                  <item>Lignum Aloes,</item>
                  <item>Maſtick,</item>
                  <item>Spikenard, of each half a dragme,</item>
               </list>
               <p>
                  <hi>Preſerved Citron Pills 3 dragms, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves of Borage and Roſemary, of each 6 dragms: make them all into a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection with Sugar Decocted in Fennel
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:119681:57"/>
and Roſe-water; and take hereof as you have occaſion.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Tabulats to ſtrengthen the ſight.</head>
               <p>Take Species Diambrae a dragme and a half, Eye-bright, Celendine, Fennel, Vervain, of each one ſcruple; Seeds of Rue, and Silver Mountain, of each half a dragme, Sugar 5 ounces; boyl them all in Eye-bright water, and make Tabulats thereof, whereof take one every night after ſupper.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>An excellent Water for the Eyes.</head>
               <p>Take the Waters of Rue, Celendine, and Eye-bright, of each 2 ounces; Fen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel and the Juyce of Vervain, of each 1 ounce; the Gall of a Pickerel three dragms, Lignum-Aloes beaten ſmall, half a dragme: The Seeds of Rue, of Celendine, and Marjoram Gentle, of each one dragme; put them together in a glaſſe cloſe ſtopt, and luted with Dough: Let it ſtand a day in an Oven after the Bread is taken out; the next day take of the paſt, and ſet it 12 dayes in the Sun; ſtrain it, and keep it in a
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:119681:57"/>
glaſſe cloſe ſtopt for your uſe: when you will uſe it, put a drop thereof into the Eyes morning and evening, lying on your back.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Potion to purge for a weak ſight.</head>
               <p>Take Treacle half a dragme; mix it with white-Wine, Water of Rue or Fennel: take it once a week.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Powder to ſtrengthen the ſight.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>Take Eye-bright half an ounce,</item>
                  <item>Caraway ſodden in Vinegar and dryed, and Marjoram Gentle <hi>3.</hi> quarters of an ounce,</item>
                  <item>Lignum Aloes,</item>
                  <item>Spica Indiae, of each <hi>1</hi> ounce,</item>
                  <item>Sorrel Seeds <hi>5</hi> ſcruples,</item>
                  <item>Coriander prepared,</item>
                  <item>Cinamon,</item>
                  <item>Fennel, of each <hi>2</hi> dragms,</item>
               </list>
               <p>
                  <hi>Make thereof a Powder with Sugar as much as you pleaſe, And hereof you may take a dragme after Supper, with a little Julip of Roſes.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:119681:58"/>
               <head>A Medicine to ſtrengthen the ſight, and for thoſe that be purblind.</head>
               <p>Take the Liver of a Buck, take out the Gall, and cut the Liver in pieces, laying thereon whole long Pepper: cover it with another piece of Liver, and Pepper, as before; thus continuing till all the pieces be layd one upon another, and above and beneath be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but Liver: put this in an Oven, and dry it well; then take off the Pep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, beat it ſmall, and mix ſome Musk amongſt it; And with the moiſture that droppeth from the Liver, moiſten the Powder, and make Lozenges thereof, And keep them till you have occaſion for to uſe it; then temper it with Eye-bright water, and eat thereof two or three mornings together.</p>
               <p>In all diſeaſes &amp; infirmities of the eyes whatſoever, have a ſpecial reſpect unto your dyet, avoyd Salt and groſſe meats, ſtrong drinks and venery, eſpecially ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe in either: uſe temperance and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration in all things, for <hi>in mediocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate ſalus.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="99" facs="tcp:119681:58"/>
            <head>The Mirrour of HEALTH. Of Aches, Meagrims, and other Diſeaſes in the Head.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Drink for the Head-ach.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>AKE Betony, Vervain, Worm-wood, Celen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine, Walwort, Rue, Bark of an Elder Tree, Honey and Pepper, of each equal parts; ſtamp them together, and ſeeth them in Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and drink thereof morning and evening.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
               <p>Take Rue, Vervain, Worm-wood, Sage, Walwort, Alehoof, red Fennel, Planten, inner rinde of Elder, of each a handful; ſtamp them ſmall, and put them
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:119681:59"/>
in a new earthen pot, with a quarter of an ounce of Pepper in Powder; put thereto a Pottle of red Wine, and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Stale Ale, and ſeeth it till half be conſumed: ſtrain it, and drink there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of 8 ſpoonfulls at a time, 9 mornings together: And waſh thy Head with this liquour following.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Water for the Head-ach.</head>
               <p>Take Rue, Alehoof, Betony, Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vain, Mints, red Fennel, Worm-wood, Southern-wood, of each a handful; waſh them, and ſhred them ſmall, and ſeeth them in Water in an earthen pot, and waſh thy Head with ſome of the Water; and mix the Herbs with wheat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bran, and apply it to the mold of the Head as hot as may be ſuffered, bin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding it on with a Cloth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To cleanſe the Head, Breaſt and Stomack, and cauſe a good appetite.</head>
               <p>Take 3 handfulls of Centaury, and ſeeth it in a Gallon of Water, till half be conſumed: then ſtrain it, and put to it a pinte of clarifyed Honey: then ſeeth
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:119681:59"/>
it ſoftly to a quart, and drink thereof two ſpoonfulls, morning and night, firſt and laſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To ceaſe Aches and ſwellings cauſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d of Sores and Wounds in the Head.</head>
               <p>Take Mallows, Worm-wood, Mug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wort, Betony, and Egrimony, of each a handful: waſh them, and ſtamp them, &amp; put thereto 3 ounces of fine wheat-Flower, as much Honey, and as much barrows Greaſe; ſtamp them together, and put thereto red Wine a little quantity, and fry them, and lay them warm to the ſore; but lay a Colewort-leaf between the Plaiſter and the wound, and it will ceaſe the ach, and put away the ſwelling.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For the Meagrim in the Head, Impoſthume, Dropſie, Feaver, and all Aches in the Head.</head>
               <p>Take 4 penny weight of the Root of Pellitory of Spain, a half penny weight of Spikenard, and grinde them, and boyl them in good Vinegar; and when it is cold, put thereto a ſpoonful of
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:119681:60"/>
Honey, &amp; a Sawcer full of Muſtard, and mingle them well together; and hold thereof in thy mouth a ſpoonful at once, as long as a man may be ſaying 2 <hi>Creeds, (if you have not forgot how to ſay the Creed)</hi> then ſpit it out into a Veſſel, and take more: and do ſo 9 or 10 times together. Take it after Dinner, and going to bed, and waſh thy mouth after it: and uſe this Medicine 3 dayes toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. <hi>Probatum.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For the Meagrim.</head>
               <p>Take Galingale half a dragme, Gin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger one dragme, Nutmegs half a dragm, Cloves two dragmes, Elecampane two dragmes, Annis a dragme, Licoris and Sugar, of each half a dragme; make them all into fine powder, and take thereof a dragme, firſt and laſt in ſome Betony Water.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For the Head-ach, that proceedeth from hot and Cholerick cauſes.</head>
               <p>If heat be the cauſe of the Head-ach, it is known by the ſwiftneſs of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tients
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:119681:60"/>
pulſe, redneſs of the Urine, much thirſt, dry'th of the Mouth, Tongue and Noſtrils; no ſleep, little appetite to meat, heat over all the Body.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Outward Applications for the Head-ach, proceeding from hot cauſes.</head>
               <p>Take Oil of Roſes, Roſe-water, and Vinegar of Roſes, of each a like quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity; dip double linen Cloths herein, and lay them to the temples and the fore-head; refreſhing and changing them again as often as it dryeth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another for the ſame, more ſtrong.</head>
               <p>If the heat be very extream, take the Water of Nymphea, called in Engliſh white water Lilleys, water of Endive, of each 3 ounces, Saunders red, white, and yellow, of each one dragme; or elſe 3 dragmes of one of them, if you cannot get them all three; Roſe leaves beaten half a dragme, beaten Camphire half a dragm; mix them all together, and uſe them as the other.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="104" facs="tcp:119681:61"/>If there be any flux of the Belly, or ague, that cauſeth the Head-ach, then for young or weak perſons you may uſe theſe Medicines following, with good effect: Such as are Caſſia, Manna. Syrrup of Roſes, or Sene-Leaves, boy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with ſome cooling Herbs: more ſtronger Bodyes may purge with Pill Cochiae, or the like ſtrong purge, if they have no looſeneſs with it.</p>
               <p>If there be any great flux or looſeneſs of the Body, then let the Patient avoyd light and looſening meats; but boyl his meat in ſteeled water, which is thus made: Take as much fair water as you intend to uſe; ſet it on the fire: then take a good peece of Steel, heat it red hot in the fire, then quench it in the Water; repeating it over three or four times; So likewiſe may you Steel Milk or Wine, and prepare Gold, Silver, or flints for the ſame purpoſe: but if the Patient hath no looſeneſs, then you may ſoon prepare for him this Decocti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on following.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="105" facs="tcp:119681:61"/>
               <head>Drink for the Head-ach.</head>
               <p>Take Sene-Leaves 1 ounce, Cina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, Anniſeeds, Fennel-Seeds, and Currans, of each one dragme, Licoris two dragmes, ſweet Marjoram and Roſemary, of both half a handful, two or three Figges; boyl them all in a quart of water with one ounce of Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, till half be conſumed: then ſtrain it; And for the Doſe, give hereof to a Child 2 ounces at a time; or weak Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons: to ſtronger Bodyes, 4 ounces.</p>
               <p>If there be pain in the Head, and the Body bound endeavour, the firſt thing you do, to open and make it ſoluble: otherwiſe the aſcention of vapours unto the brain, will ſo diſtemper the Head with heat and pain, that phren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, raging and madneſs will enſue: to do this, uſe Clyſters, Purgations, and ſome purging Potions and Suppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="106" facs="tcp:119681:62"/>
               <head>A Clyſter, to provoke the Body to go to Stool.</head>
               <p>Take Mallows 3 handfulls, Beets and Herb Mercury, of each two hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulls; boyl them well together in fair water, then ſtrain them: Then take 12 ounces of this Decoction; three yolks of Egges, Oil of Seſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum or Linſeed 4 ounces, Salgem half a dragme; temper them together, and miniſter it warm.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another.</head>
               <p>Take Mutton-broth, Veal-broth, or Hen-broth, of either of them 16 ounces; melt therein freſh Butter and Ducks-Greaſe, of each one ounce, Saffron half a dragme, Oil of Lilleys, and Oil of Dill, of each one ounce and a half, Indie-Salt one dragme: then temper them together, and adminiſter it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="107" facs="tcp:119681:62"/>
               <head>A Decoction to open the Body for the ſame.</head>
               <p>Take 12 Prunes, Licorice, Currans, Annis-ſeeds, and Fennel, of each half an ounce, Flowers of Burrage and Bugloſſe, of each one dragme and a half: boyl them in a quart of water till a third part be waſted; ſtrain it, and drink thereof.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another for the ſame, and to coole the Body.</head>
               <p>Take Currans, Licorice, Prunes, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jubes, Violets, Barley, Melon-ſeed, Pompeon-ſeed, Gourd-ſeed, and Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumber-ſeed, of each one quarter of an ounce; boyl them as the other.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Pills for the Head-ach.</head>
               <p>Take Rhabarb 2 drames, Maſtick one ſcruple, Scammony half a dragm make them into Pills with Juyce of Rue, one dragme of them at a time.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="108" facs="tcp:119681:63"/>
               <head>A ſweet Ball or perfume for the Head-ach.</head>
               <p>Take Violets, Water Lilleys, Willow Leaves, Roſes, of each one ounce; Camphire 2 grains: beat them all toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and bind them up in a piece of fine Silk, and wet it often in Roſe-water, and ſmell often to it.</p>
               <p>If the Head-ach proceed from a cold cauſe, it is good to uſe Gargariſmes, to draw forth the Rheume out of the Head: for which this following is effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Gargariſme for the Head-ach.</head>
               <p>Take Maſtick, Calamus, Licorice, Currans, of each half an ounce, Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſop, Ireos, of each 2 drams, Pellitoty of Spain, Ginger, Saxifrage, Muſtard-Seeds, of each one dram: beat them all together, and boyl them in freſh Water, and gargle the mouth there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with three or four times a day, warm.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="109" facs="tcp:119681:63"/>
               <head>A Clyſter for the ſame.</head>
               <p>Take Mallows, Herb Mercury, Dill, Rue, Bran, of each one handfull; boyl them in a ſufficient quantity of Water: take of thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Collature 12 or 16 ounces; mix with it <hi>Hyera Picra,</hi> and white Sugar, of each half an ounce, Salt two dragmes, Oil of Dill and Rue, of each one ounce and a half, and give it warm.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Conſerve for the Head-ach.</head>
               <p>Take Conſerve of Roſes 2 ounces and a half, Conſerve of Betony one ounce and a half, Cinamon, Cloves, Annis-ſeeds, of each one dragm, green Ginger half an ounce, Syrrup of Citrons a ſufficient quantity to make it into an Electuary; and take thereof every morning the quantity of a Nut.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another for the ſame, called <hi>Electua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium Vitis.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Take Currans 6 ounces, Licorice 2
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:119681:64"/>
dragmes: boyl theſe in the Waters of Bugloſſe, Scabious and Betony, of each 12 ounces; then ſtrain it out hard, and ſteep in the liquour warm 1 dragme of Rhabarbe, Lavender 5 grains, bound up together in a Cloth: ſtop it cloſe, and boyl it a good while in <hi>Balneo;</hi> then ſtrain it out, and add to it as much Rhabarbe and Spike as before, and let it ſteep therein a night: ſtrain it again; and then put therein one ounce of the Barks of yellow Mirobalaus: then boyl it a little more, and ſtrain it, and add to the Collature 6 ounces of Sugar, and two ounces of Manna, and boyl it to a Syrrup; when it is almoſt cold, mingle in it half an ounce of Cinamon, Cloves, Galingale and Nutmegs, of each one dragme, Seeds of Fennel and Annis, of each half an ounce: boyl them up to an Electuary, and keep it for your uſe for the purpoſes before recited.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A good Drink for a Head-ach of cold.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Take Bugloſſe Roots</hi> 1 <hi>handful,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Chicory Roots,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Harts-Tongue,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <pb n="111" facs="tcp:119681:64"/>
                     <hi>Flowers of Bugloſſe,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Borage,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Roſes, of each half a handful.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Boyl them all in 4 quarts of white-Wine, a quarter of an hour: when it is cold, ſtrain it, and add to it 4 quarts of white-Wine more; and ſteep in it Sage-Leaves and Roſemary, of each half a handful, long Pepper, Galingale, Cloves, Cubebs, of each half an ounce; Currans, Cinamon and Coriander-Seeds prepared, of each one ounce; groſly beaten, and tyed up all together in a Cloth: boyl the Wine 3 or 4 walms, and put up the Wine in a Rund<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let, and drink thereof as you pleaſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Powder for a cold pain, and Rheume in the Head.</head>
               <p>Take Nutmegs, Mace, Roſemary, Cloves, Frankincenſe, Maſtick, Laven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, Myrrhe, Marjoram and Stechas, of each a like quantity: beat them all to powder, and rub the Head well therewith; then cover and keep the Head warm with a Cap.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="112" facs="tcp:119681:65"/>
               <head>A Lotion or Water, to Bath and Waſh the feet for the Head-ach.</head>
               <p>Take Betony, Roſes, Elder Flowers, Sage, Camomile, and Marjoram, of each 4 handfulls, Bran 2 handfulls, as much Lavender; ſeeth them all together in a ſufficient quantity of Water, and bath the Feet in it every night very hot, hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding them in it about half an hour; and every three dayes caſt away the old bath, and make freſh.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For Deafneſs.</head>
               <p>Take Betony and Horehound, and ſtamp them in a Morter, and ſtrain out the Juyce; and drop thereof into the Patients Ear, when he is going to bed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
               <p>Take a round piece of an Aſh-Tree with the bark on, and lay the midſt thereof in the fire, and keep the Water that droppeth out at both ends; and take the Juyce of Monks Rhabarbe,
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:119681:65"/>
white-Wine, and the fat of freſh Eel; of each a like quantity: mingle them all together, and put a drop or two there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of into the Patients Ears when he goes to bed; uſe it every night.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
               <p>Take the Gall of a Weather, and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, of each a like portion, and mingle them together, and put it into the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tients Ears.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For Pain in the Ears.</head>
               <p>Purge the Head with Syrrup of Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, Caſſia, and Electuary <hi>de Succo Roſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum;</hi> Then oftentimes take Oil of Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, Oil of Water-Lillies, and Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans Milk, and drop thereof into the Ears.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another for pains in the Ears.</head>
               <p>Take the Juyce of Strawberry-leaves, of Pauls Betony, Sage and Houſleek, of each one ounce; Maſtick and Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kincenſe a dragm and a half, of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction of Cole-worts two ounces;
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:119681:66"/>
temper them all together, and drop thereof into the Ear.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Againſt Noiſe and Hiſſing, or Singing in the Ears.</head>
               <p>Deafneſs uſually follows after this, if not timely prevented: which to do, it is neceſſary to purge the Brains with Pills <hi>de Hyera, Maſtichine, Cochie,</hi> or <hi>Hyera cum Agarico;</hi> either or all of which you may have at the Apotheca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries: take of one of theſe Pills a dragme at a time: If you take of the Pill Maſtichine, you may take a dragme thereof, and form it into ſix little Pills more or leſſe, according as you can ſwallow them, and take them at night going to bed; if you take of any of the other Pills, take a dragme thereof in the morning.</p>
               <p>Afterwards take this Decoction which follows; and let the fume or hot vapour thereof aſcend into the Ears.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="115" facs="tcp:119681:66"/>
               <head>A Fumigation for Noiſe in the Ears.</head>
               <p>Take Marjoram, Mints, Worm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood, Roſemary, Sage, Betony and Camomile, of each half a handful; boyl them in a ſufficient quantity of Water, till half be conſumed, and let the fume or hot vapour thereof aſcend into the Ears.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To ſtanch bleeding at the Noſe.</head>
               <p>Take the Seeds of the Hazel-Tree, and burn them to powder, and let the Patient have ſome of it blown into his Noſe through a quill, and let him drink the Juyce of Planten.</p>
               <p>The Juyce of Planten, or Planten-Water and Milk made into a poſſet, ſtanch and heal any bleeding in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To Ripen an Impoſthume in the Ear.</head>
               <p>Take fine wheat Flower one ounce and a half, the Muſcilage of Linſeed, and Fenegreek Seed, Eels-Greaſe, Litharge of Gold, Ceruſe and Frankin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe,
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:119681:67"/>
of each one dragme: mix them all together, and make a Plaiſter there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and lay it all over the Ear, and rub it into the Ear.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
               <p>Take freſh Holly-hock Roots beaten ſmall two ounces, Linſeed, and Fene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greek Seeds beaten, of each one ounce; Dill-Seed and Camomile, of each half an ounce; boyl them in Butter to the conſiſtence of a ſoft Plaiſter, and lay it to the Ear.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To draw out the matter, cleanſe and heal an Impoſthume in the Ear.</head>
               <p>When the Impoſthume is ripe, and begins to break, then to cleanſe and heal the ſame, uſe this Unguent follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
               <p>Take Sarcocolla, Aloes, Dragons-blood, Myrrhe, and Frankincenſe, Iron Droſſe, and Verdigreaſe, of each half a dragme: incorporate them all well to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with Vinegar; and dip a taint therein, and put it into the Ear.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:119681:67"/>
               <head>Another for all kinds of Imposthumes in the Ears.</head>
               <p>Take Honey 5 dragmes, Vinegar half an ounce, Verdigreaſe 1 dragme bruiſed ſmall; ſeeth them together, then dip Wool therein, and lay it into the impoſthumated Ear.</p>
               <p>The Oyntment called <hi>Unguentum, Apoſtolorum,</hi> which is to be had at the Apothecaries, is alſo good for Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſthumes in the Ears, to be uſed as the former.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For the Tooth-ach.</head>
               <p>Take Allum and Brimſtone, of each what quantity you pleaſe thereof; burn them on a Tyle-ſtone, and make pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der thereof; and add thereto powder of Pepper a like quantity: ſtamp them all together with a Clove of Garlick; then ty them up in a little piece of linen, and lay it between the Teeth where the pain is.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="118" facs="tcp:119681:68"/>
               <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
               <p>Take Honey and ſeeth it, and take off the ſcum as it ariſeth, and put thereto powder of Pepper, and ſeeth it till it be black: then put ſome of it on a Sage leaf; lay it to the aking Teeth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
               <p>Take Vinegar, Muſtard, powder of Pepper, and Pellitory of Spain, of each what quantity you pleaſe, the Kernel of a Gal-nut; boyl them all together, and if the Teeth be hollow, put there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of into the Teeth; or elſe lay it hot to the Gums.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Tooth-ach that cometh of Worms.</head>
               <p>If there be Worms in the Gums, as it often happens there are, which cauſe much pain in the Teeth, and do impoſthumate and periſh them; to kill them,</p>
               <p>Take Pepper and beat it to powder,
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:119681:68"/>
and temper it with good Wine; and ſup thereof warm, and hold it in thy mouth till it be cold, and then ſpit it out: uſe this often, and thou ſhalt be delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of all anguiſh in the Teeth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another to faſten looſe Teeth.</head>
               <p>Take Harts-horn and burn it, and put the aſhes that come thereof in a linen cloth and lay it to the Teeth, and it will make them faſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To make a Tooth fall out of it ſelf.</head>
               <p>Take the tallow of a Ram, and Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, and ſtamp them together, and anoynt the Teeth therewith, and it will fall out of its own accord.</p>
               <p>Turner. <hi>So ſays my Author Verbatim, I do not deviate from him: the Medicine is eaſy to be made: if it do no good, I am ſure it can do no hurt; if you have occaſion, you may ſoon try it.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="120" facs="tcp:119681:69"/>
               <head>Here follows another receipt for the ſame purpoſe, which you may uſe as you like it; it will not cost you much.</head>
               <p>Take a water-Frogge, and a green Frogge, and ſeeth them together: ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Greaſe that ariſeth, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with anoynt thy Gum, and the aking Teeth: <hi>I do not like this, ſo well as the former.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For ſtinking Teeth.</head>
               <p>Take two handfulls of Cumin-ſeed, and ſeeth it in white-Wine, and let them waſh their Teeth therewith.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To make Teeth white.</head>
               <p>Take Honey, Salt, and Rye-meal, of each what quantity you pleaſe; and therewith rub thy Teeth and Gums.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For an Impoſthume in the Gums.</head>
               <p>Take Honey of Roſes one ounce and a half, Vinegar half an ounce; mix
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:119681:69"/>
them together, and therewith gargle the mouth: when you ſpit it out, take in freſh again; uſing it often.</p>
               <p>Likewiſe it is good to open the Gums if there be any ſores: and waſh it three times a day with water, wherein Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lom, Myrrhe, and Salt have been ſodden.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
               <p>Take half a pinte of the Water of Knot-graſſe, and half an ounce of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lom; diſſolve the Allom in the Water, and therewith waſh the Teeth and Gums.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For loſſe of Speech.</head>
               <p>Take the Juyce of Southern-wood, Sage, and Pimpernel, and put it under thy Tongue; or take the Juyce of Wormwood, and temper it with Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney; and let the Patient hold it in his mouth.</p>
               <p>The voyce is oftentimes ſpoiled, and corrupted by hoarſeneſs, or weakened by long ſickneſs; for which this Electu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary which follows is very good.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="122" facs="tcp:119681:70"/>
               <head>An Electuary for loſſe of Speech.</head>
               <p>Take <hi>Ireos</hi> half an ounce, Penny-Royal, Hyſop, Licoris, of each 3 drag, Dragagant, bitter Almonds, Kernels of Pine-apples, Cinamon, Ginger and Pepper, of each one dragme and a half, Figges, Dates, Currans; of each one ſcruple, red Styrax 3 ſcruples and a half; cut the fruits ſmall, beat all the reſt to powder, and to every ounce of this powder add 12 ounces of Sugar: make it into an Electuary with Honey or Syrrup of Hyſop; or if you pleaſe, you may make Lozengs thereof.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
               <p>Take <hi>Ireos</hi> half an ounce, Sugar-Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy a dragm, Cinamon, Ginger and Pep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per one dragme, Sugar 12 ounces; boyl it in Hyſop-Water, to the thickneſs of an Electuary; then make Lozengs there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: theſe are good for a Cough, a cold Rheume, and a wheezing breath.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="123" facs="tcp:119681:70"/>
               <head>Againſt Hoarſeneſs, a dry Cough, and all infections of the Lungs, and Breaſt, proceeding of heat and dry'th; from whence a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption follows.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Take Dragagant</hi> 1 <hi>ounce,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Gum Arabick</hi> 5 <hi>dragms,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Starch</hi> 2 <hi>dragmes,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Licoris,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Melon-Seeds,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Gourd-Seeds,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Pompeon-Seeds,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Cucumber-Seeds, of each</hi> 1 <hi>drag.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Camphire</hi> 5 <hi>dragmes,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Sugar Pennets one ounce and a half.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Beat all theſe to powder, and add to an ounce of this powder, 12 ounces of fine Sugar; and boyl it in Violet water unto a Confection, or make Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zenges of it, if you pleaſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="124" facs="tcp:119681:71"/>
               <head>A hot Confection for a tough, flegma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick, and ſlymy Cough; ſo that the Patient cannot get up any thing, for a wheezing and ſhort Breath.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Take Dragagant,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Hyſop, of each</hi> 2 <hi>ounces,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Kernells of Pine-Apples,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Sweet Almonds,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Linſeed, of each</hi> 3 <hi>dragmes,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Fenegreek,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Cinamon, of each</hi> 2 <hi>dragmes,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Juyce of Licoris,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Ginger, of each one dragme.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Boyl them all into an Electuary, or Confection, as the other; or if you will, you may make Lozengs thereof: and every night when you go to bed, diſſolve one of them in ſweet-Wine, and add half a ſcruple of Saffron unto it: this comforts the Heart, and vital Spirits.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="125" facs="tcp:119681:71"/>
               <head>A Drink for the ſame.</head>
               <p>Take five pints of fair Water, half a pinte of Honey, ſix Figges, one ounce of Currans, 2 dragmes of Licorice; boyl it till one pinte be waſted, and drink thereof every morning faſting, a good Cup full warm.</p>
               <p>To make the voyce cleer, an Electuary.
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Take Cabbage-Seeds,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Hyſop,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Elecampane Roots,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Colts-foot,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Roots of Flower De luce,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Horehound, of each half an ounce,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Annis-Seeds,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Fennel-Seeds,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Ameos,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Cubebs,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Ariſtolochy, of each one dragme and a half,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Sugar Pennets</hi> 3 <hi>dragmes,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Oxymel Compoſitum,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Syrrup of Horehound, of each</hi> 3 <hi>ounc.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Pine-apple Kernells</hi> 4 <hi>ounces,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Saffron</hi> 1 <hi>dragme.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="126" facs="tcp:119681:72"/>Make them all together into a Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction or Electuary, with 12 ounces of Honey clarifyed: take hereof about 2 dragmes morning and night, in a little of the Decoction of Nettle-Roots, mixing a little Sugar with it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For them that ſpeak in their ſleep.</head>
               <p>Take the Juyce of Southern-wood 1 ſpoonfull; and temper it in Wine, and drink it going to bed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
               <p>Take the Tops of Rue and Vervain, of each a like quantity; drink the Juyce thereof in Wine, going to bed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For them that ſpit Bloud.</head>
               <p>Take Smallage, Rue, Betony, Mynts and Planten<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of each a like quantity, boyl them in good new Milk, and drink thereof warm.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="127" facs="tcp:119681:72"/>
               <head>For a ſtinking Breath.</head>
               <p>Take Butter, the Juyce of Moon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wort, and the Juyce of Fetherfew; of each a like quantity: temper them with Honey, and give the Patient every morning a ſpoonfull thereof.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
               <p>Take two handfulls of Cumin-Seeds, and beat it to powder; and boyl it well in white-Wine, and drink of this decocted Wine 15 dayes toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, every morning, ſweetned with a little Sugar.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
               <p>Take three handfulls of Cumin, Vervain, Mynts and Rue, of each three handfulls, Licoris 1 dragme, Ginger and Nutmegs; of each half an ounce: bruiſe them all in a Morter, then boyl them in a Gallon of white-Wine till half be waſted: Drink thereof morning and evening, firſt and laſt, for 15 dayes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, as hot as you can ſuffer it. <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batum.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="128" facs="tcp:119681:73"/>
               <head>For a cold and Cough.</head>
               <p>Take Hyſop, Roſemary, Planten, and Radiſh Roots; of each a like quantity, and boyl them in white-Wine from a Pottle to a quart; then poer out the Liquor, and put the Herbs into a Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and mingle them well together, bruiſing them, and ſtrain them into the Liquor again: then take a pinte of Life-Honey, and boyl it and ſcum it, and put thereto a quarter of a pound of May-Butter that is clarified; and let it ſeeth together by the ſpace that one may ſay the Pſalm of <hi>Miſerere mei Deus, (that is, the</hi> 51 <hi>Pſalme in Engliſh, called in</hi> thoſe dayes one of the 7 Penitential <hi>Pſalms:</hi> but now penitency is out of <hi>faſhion. The Pſalm will not hurt you, if you think it not too much ſuperſtition to read it; neither will your Reading it do the Pſalm any hurt at all;</hi> nor your <hi>letting it alone, will not alter its Religion.</hi>) Then ſtrain it through a linen Cloth, and take the <hi>Collature,</hi> (that is, the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor or Medicine, thus compounded,) and reſerve it in a glaſſe Veſſel cloſe ſtopt, And let the Patient take a little
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:119681:73"/>
thereof firſt and laſt, in a draught of ſtale Ale, warm, till it be whole; for this is a proved Medicine; <hi>ſaith my Author</hi> in <hi>Haec Verba.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For a Man or Woman that hath great ſickneſs in the ſides, and cannot well draw their wind, nor Cough, for pain.</head>
               <p>Take Hill-wort, Alexander, Parſly, Lovage, Smallage, red Fennel, Burnet, Grommel; of each a like quantity, ſeeth them in ſufficient quantity of white-Wine till half be waſted: And let the Patient Drink thereof hot, firſt and laſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For a Cough.</head>
               <p>Take the Juyce of Sage, and Rue, and Hyſop; of each a like quantity, of Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min, Pepper, Licorice, and ſweet Fen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel Seeds in powder; of each a like quantity: ſeeth them all in clarified Honey, ſufficient to make an Electuary thereof, and let the Patient take there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of morning and evening.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="130" facs="tcp:119681:74"/>
               <head>Of the Tumor or ſwelling in the Throat, called the Squinancy.</head>
               <p>This is a dangerous Diſeaſe, that co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth about the Troat-Boll, and ſhut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth up the inward parts of the Throat, ſo that thereby the breath is ſtopt: which commonly proceedeth of groſſe humours, that fall from the Head into the Throat; which is alſo increaſed by ſleeping immediately after meals. The Patient if he feel this infirmity ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proching, ought to purge his Head well with Pill Elephanginae, eat and drink but little, and to eat light meats, and Gargarize his mouth with Wine of Pomgranates and Barley-Water min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled together.</p>
               <p>Alſo take Syrrup of Poppeys, and Syrrup of Mulberryes, of each one dragme, Roſe-water 3 ounces: temper them together, and uſe them as the other before. But to conclude;</p>
               <p>Take Album Graecum, <hi>Anglicè,</hi> a white Doggs Turd; beat it to powder, and mix it with Syrrup of Mulberryes, Black-berryes, or Honey, and give it to the Patient to ſwallow by little and little. <hi>Probatum.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="131" facs="tcp:119681:74"/>
               <head>To ſtrengthen the Memory; an Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Johannes Coletus,</hi> taught him by a Jew. A Gargariſme to cleanſe the Head for the Memory.</head>
               <p>TAke Pieretrum, Marjoram, Galin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gale, Ginger, Caraway, Broad Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten-Seed, and Muſtard-Seed; beat them groſſe together, and put two ounces of this powder to one quart of Water, into a Veſſel cloſe ſtopt, and boyl it in Balneo; then when it hath well ſodden, put a quart of ſtrong Wine to it, and an ounce of cleer Honey; and let it ſeeth again till about a pint of the Liquor be waſted: herewith gargarize the mouth well, and many times toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, every morning, holding it hot a good while in the mouth, that the fume may aſcend up into the Head; but uſe it only, when the Moon is increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="132" facs="tcp:119681:75"/>
               <head>Then uſe this Drink for the Memory, to draw ſuperfluous Moiſture out of the Head.</head>
               <p>Take Ginger, long Pepper; of each one dragme, Galingale one ſcruple, Cloves, Cubebs, of each one dragme and a half: beat them all together to powder, and ty them up in a linen Cloth, and boyl them in Balneo, in a pot cloſe ſtopt, with 2 quarts of Wine: then let it ſtand covered till it be cleer; then drink a good draught thereof, morning and going to bed.</p>
               <p>Kemb your Head a good while toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the Sun, or by the fire, as the ſeaſon of the year is, to open the pores: then waſh your Head with Rue-Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and drink a draught of Wine after it, and eat a bit of bread ſteeped in the Wine: eat light ſuppers, be moderate in your ſleep and dyet: And continue this uſe many dayes together; And then anoynt the Head and Temples with this Oyntment following.</p>
               <p>Take white Lillyes, Colewort-Leaves, Balm; of each one dragme: pound them together, and put them in
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:119681:75"/>
a pot: pour therein 2 ounces of Sallet-Oil, freſh Butter as much as all the reſt, Spirit of Wine 4 times rectified, 3 ſpoonfuls of water of Rue, Sage, and Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lendine, of each 2 ſpoonfulls, white-Wine 5 ſpoonfuls: incorporate and mix them all well together; then ſet them 6 or 8 hours in a warm place, ſtrain it, and ſeeth the liquour till it be as thick as Honey, and ſet it in the Sun afterwards, till it look red as Copper. This Salve will keep two years. The beſt time to make it, is about <hi>June.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And after the Head is purged as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is directed, anoynt the hinder parts of the Head &amp; Temples with this Salve; and keep the Head warm with a leather Cap, that it may have the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter operation; waſh the Head with warm Wine at night; let your meat be eaſy of digeſtion, and eſpecially for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear exceſſive drinking: uſe this at firſt four dayes together, and then two or three dayes together, every eight weeks for a year, every three months the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond year; and once every year after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, as long as you live: Let the Moon be increaſing when you uſe it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="134" facs="tcp:119681:76"/>
               <head>A Potion to procure ſteep in Frantick people.</head>
               <p>Take white Poppey-ſeeds half an ounce, Roots of Mandragora, Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bane-ſeeds; of each half a dragme, Saffron 4 grains: bruiſe them all toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and bind them up in a Cloth; then ſteep them 6 hours in 5 ounces of Water-Lilleys: then ſtrain it, and give to the Patient of this water, from one ounce to three, according to the quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Diſeaſe, and ſtrength of the party.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
               <p>Take 12 ounces of Water-Lilleys, <hi>Opium</hi> one dragme; ſteep them toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in 3 pints of Malmſey 24 hours: then caſt therein one quarter of an ounce of Salt, as much Henbane-ſeeds, Lettice-ſeed 3 dragms: and diſtill it in <hi>Balneo;</hi> and give hereof from half a dragme to a dragme, at night when the Patient goes to bed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="135" facs="tcp:119681:76"/>
               <head>An Oyntment or Salve to cauſe ſleep.</head>
               <p>Take one ounce of <hi>Poplar Salve,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">That is the Oyntment, which the Apothecary calls <hi>Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guentum Populeon.</hi>
                  </note> half an ounce of Oil of Violets, Henbane-ſeeds, and Mandragora Roots; of each half a dragme, Saffron, Caſſia-wood; of each one ſcruple: mix them together, and apply it to the privityes of Men, and the Breaſts of Women.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For the ſame.</head>
               <p>Take Willow-leaves, Water-Lilleys, Vine-leaves, and Lettiſe: boyl them in water, and with the Decoction bath and waſh the privy Members, hands and feet.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Clyſter againſt the ſhaking Palſey.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>Take Centaury,</item>
                  <item>Sage,</item>
                  <item>Rue,</item>
                  <item>Cowſlips.</item>
                  <item>St. Johns-wort.</item>
                  <item>Mercury; of each half a handful,</item>
                  <item>Saffron-ſeed,</item>
                  <item>
                     <pb n="136" facs="tcp:119681:77"/>
                     <hi>Rue-ſeed,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Silver Mountain-ſeed,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Baſil-ſeed; of each half an ounce,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Agarick</hi> 5 <hi>dragmes,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Stechas,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Amaranthus of each half an ounce;</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Seeth them together in ſufficient wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; then take 12 or 16 ounces of this Decoction, Honey, and Oil of Lilleys, of each one ounce and a half, Salgem, and Pill Cochiae; of each half a dragm: temper them well, and adminiſter it for a Clyſter.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Powder for the Head, against the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Palſey.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Take Field-Cypres,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Cowſlips,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Lignum Aloes,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Ireos,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Hermodactils,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Stechas,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Marjoram,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mints; of each half adragme,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Spica Indie,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Grains,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Rue, of each one ſcruple,</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>
                  <pb n="137" facs="tcp:119681:77"/>Beat every one by himſelf to a ſubtil Powder; then temper them together, and beſtrew the Head with it, when it is new ſhorn.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>An excellent Confection, which reſiſteth Poyſon, and defendeth the Heart against all Contagion and Infecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; comforteth the Stomack, &amp; helpeth the Palſey, or the trembling of the Joynts.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>Take Cynamon,</item>
                  <item>Lignum Aloes,</item>
                  <item>Cloves,</item>
                  <item>Spica Indie,</item>
                  <item>Galingale,</item>
                  <item>Licorice,</item>
                  <item>Trochis de Vialis, ſive Scammonio.</item>
                  <item>Diarrhodon Abbatis; of each <hi>5</hi> dragmes,</item>
                  <item>Nutmegs,</item>
                  <item>Aliptae Muſcatae,</item>
                  <item>Sedoary,</item>
                  <item>Spikenard,</item>
                  <item>Mace,</item>
                  <item>Rhabarbe,</item>
                  <item>Red Storax, of each half an ounce,</item>
                  <item>
                     <pb n="138" facs="tcp:119681:78"/>Pearles prepared,</item>
                  <item>Burnt Ivory,</item>
                  <item>Harts Bones,</item>
                  <item>Ginger,</item>
                  <item>Blatia by Zantia, of each <hi>2</hi> dragms and a half,</item>
                  <item>Muske,</item>
                  <item>Amber,</item>
                  <item>Cardamom,</item>
                  <item>Lovage-ſeed,</item>
                  <item>Baſil-ſeed, of each one dragme and a half,</item>
                  <item>Camphire one dragme,</item>
               </list>
               <p>
                  <hi>Make them all into a Confection, with 3 ounces of clarifyed Honey; take thereof every morning about the quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of a Nutmeg.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>You may if you pleaſe, for your bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter conveniency, make Lozenges there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, by adding 12 ounces of Sugar, boyled in Bugloſſe-water, to one ounce of the fore-mentioned ingredients.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For the dead Palſy.</head>
               <p>Take Nutmegs, ſliced Licorice, and Annis-ſeeds; of each one ounce, Piony Roots one dragme, Elecampane Roots
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:119681:78"/>
half an ounce, Spirit of VVine 16 ounc. Honey 8 ounces; mix theſe all toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and make a Conſerve thereof; and if you uſe it in VVinter, put thereto a quarter of an ounce of long Pepper, and give the Patient about a ſpoonful thereof every morning.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Pills to purge for the dead Palſy.</head>
               <p>Take Agarick one ſcruple, Aſſa-Faeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da half a ſcruple, Ginger 13 grains, Diagrydion 1 grain; make Pills there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of with the Juyce of Hyſop; and after the Patient is purged, let him take this Drink following for eight dayes toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p>Take Egrimony-water, and Southern-wood-water, of each 2 ounces, and ſweeten it with Sugar: Drink it in the morning, and faſt four hours after it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Syrrup for the dead Palſy.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>Take Calmus half an ounce,</item>
                  <item>Cowſlips <hi>3</hi> handfuls,</item>
                  <item>St. Johns-wort,</item>
                  <item>Sage,</item>
                  <item>Betony,</item>
                  <item>
                     <pb n="140" facs="tcp:119681:79"/>Balm,</item>
                  <item>Rue,</item>
                  <item>Bayleaves, of each one handful,</item>
                  <item>Silver Mountain,</item>
                  <item>Balſam-wood,</item>
                  <item>Balſam fruit,</item>
                  <item>Bazil-ſeed, of each <hi>2</hi> dragms,</item>
                  <item>Licorice,</item>
                  <item>Currans,</item>
                  <item>Lavender Flowers,</item>
                  <item>Amaranthus, of each one ounce,</item>
               </list>
               <p>
                  <hi>Boyl all theſe together into a Syrrup, with ſix ounces of clarifyed Honey, and a pint of Rain-water clarifyed with the white of an Egge.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Clyſter for the dead Palſey.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Take Sage,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Rue,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Stechas,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mallows,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Centory,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mercury,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Bran, of each half a handful,</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Seeth them all together: then take 12 ounces of this Decoction, of mix there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:119681:79"/>
                  <hi>Hyera Logodion</hi> half an ounce, Salt one quarter of an ounce, Sallet-Oil 3 ounces; miniſter it warm.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Powder to ſtrew on the Patients meat, in ſtead of ſpice, that hath the dead Palſey.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>Take Cynamon <hi>1</hi> ounce and a half.</item>
                  <item>Coriander,</item>
                  <item>Cloves,</item>
                  <item>Galingale,</item>
                  <item>Pepper,</item>
                  <item>Cubebs,</item>
                  <item>Mace,</item>
                  <item>Nutmegs,</item>
                  <item>Saffron, of each one ounce,</item>
                  <item>Calmus <hi>2</hi> ounces,</item>
                  <item>Coutchenel half an ounce.</item>
               </list>
               <p>
                  <hi>Temper them all to a fine powder with 6 ounces of fine Sugar.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A bath for the dead Palſey.</head>
               <p>Take Bay-berryes, Juniper-berryes, and Pepper; of each as much as you will: beat them to powder, and ſet the Patient in a dry bath, and poure of
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:119681:80"/>
this powder on hot Irons tempered with Lavender-Water; and let him ſweat well with the vapour thereof, then rub all the infected Members with Venice Soap till the Soap be drye: And after the Patient cometh out of the bath, keep him in a warm place, and rub the lame Joynts hard with Deers-ſuet.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>An Oyntment for the dead Palſey, Cramp and cold Gout.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Take Squills,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Rue,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Calmus,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Nettle-Roots,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Egrimony,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Cowſlips, of each one handful,</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Pound them all together, and put to it Oil of Nuts, and old Sallet-Oil; of each 12 ounc. Wine as much: ſeeth theſe all together till the moiſture be evapora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted away: then ſtrain it, and temper amongſt it Salt-Peter, Euphorbium, Pepper, Oil of Bayes, of each one ounce and a half, Galbanum, Turpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine; of each 2 ounces, VVax as much
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:119681:80"/>
as is needful to make a Salve there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; and keep it for the uſe aforeſaid.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Powder againſt the falling ſickneſs.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>Take Pearls prepared,</item>
                  <item>Harts-bones, of each <hi>1</hi> dragm.</item>
                  <item>Red Coral,</item>
                  <item>Piony-ſeeds and Roots, of each half a dragm,</item>
                  <item>Miſleden one dragme and a half,</item>
                  <item>Amber prepared <hi>2</hi> ſcruples,</item>
                  <item>White Sugar one ounce,</item>
                  <item>Six Leaves of Gold,</item>
               </list>
               <p>
                  <hi>Make them all into fine powder, and take hereof a dragme once a week in Piony-water or Broth.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Clyſter for the falling ſickneſs.</head>
               <p>Take Swines-bread, black Helle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bore, Centory, Daffadil, of each one dragme, Saffron-ſeed half an ounce: ſeeth this in a quart of water till half be conſumed: take 13 ounces of this Decoction, temper therein <hi>Hyera Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godion</hi> one ounce, Oil of Euphorbium 10 dragmes, Salgem one drame and
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:119681:81"/>
a half: mix them all together for a Clyſter.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Confection for the ſame.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>Take Diapenidium <hi>3</hi> dragmes,</item>
                  <item>Pliris Arcoticon <hi>1</hi> dragm,</item>
                  <item>Diambra half a dragm,</item>
                  <item>Cynamon <hi>1</hi> dragme and a half,</item>
                  <item>Nutmegs,</item>
                  <item>Cubebs, of each <hi>2</hi> ſcruples,</item>
                  <item>Ginger one dragm,</item>
                  <item>Sugar <hi>8</hi> ounces,</item>
               </list>
               <p>
                  <hi>Make a Confection thereof with Piony VVater.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Lozenges for the Cough and Rheume.</head>
               <p>Take white Poppey-ſeeds, Lettice-ſeeds, and Purſlain-ſeeds, of each one dragme, Dragagant, Gum-Arabick and Saffron, of each half a dragme, Opium 5 grains: pound all that is to be pounded, and make it to a dough with Syrrup of Poppey: make Lozenges ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of as big as ſmall Beanes; and let one of theſe at a time diſſolve in thy mouth: this is for hot Rheumes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="145" facs="tcp:119681:81"/>
               <head>Other Lozenges for a Cough.</head>
               <p>Take Pine-apple Kernels, ſteeped a night in Roſe-water, and bitter Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds blanched, of each 3 quarters of an ounce, Juyce of Licoris 2 ounces, powder of Licoris 3 dragmes; make Lozenges thereof with Roſe-water; they are good againſt the Cough, and raw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Throat that proceedeth thereof.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>An Oyntment for pain in the back.</head>
               <p>Take Oil of Spike, and Oil of Lilleys, of each half an ounce, Oil of Camomile and Dill, of each one ounce, Saffron, Lavender, Madder and Egrimony, of each one dragme, Maſtick and Squinant, of each one ſcruple, VVax as much as is needful to make it a Salve: herewith anoynt the back-bone.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Clyſter for a pleuriſy of heat and blood.</head>
               <p>Take 16 ounces of broth, made of a Calves-Foot, or Lambs-Head; put
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:119681:82"/>
therein one ounce of brown Sugar, the yolk of an Egge, 2 ounces of Sallet-Oil, Salt one dragme and a half: temper them together for a Clyſter.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>An Oyntment for Scabs, and breaking out in the Legges.</head>
               <p>Take the red Dock-Root, the Roots of Celendine, and Worm-wood, and the Leaves of Laurel; of each a like quantity: ſtamp them, and ſeeth them in May-Butter unto an Oyntment; ſtrain it, and keep it in a box for uſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>How the Body is to be Governed againſt Peſtilential, and infectious Ayres.</head>
               <p>The firſt and principal preſervation, is to avoyd all that may ingender any Feaver or Ague; and forbear all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of exceſſe, either of meat or drink: eat no groſſe meat, no Onyons, Leeks, Garlick, nor fruit.</p>
               <p>Abſtain from venereous actions; for that both openeth the Pores, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyeth the kind natural, and infee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleth the Spiritual Members, and the Spirits of Man.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="147" facs="tcp:119681:82"/>Alſo in time of Peſtilence ſuffer no great thirſt; and drink but meaſurably, only to ſlacken thy thirſt: and drink ſuch drinks as will abate heat, as Water of Borage, Endive, Lettice, Violets, Roſes, Scabious, Tormentil, Dittany; either mingled, or elſe ſeverally alone by themſelves: For if the Peſtilence reigne in the heat of the Summer, theſe Drinks be profitable, eſpecially for thoſe that be of a Cholerick Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion.</p>
               <p>Alſo when you ſleep, either in the afternoons, or at night a-bed, ſhut your Chamber-doors and Windowes cloſe, and caſt on a Pan of Coles, this Powder following.</p>
               <p>Take of Laurel-Leaves, and Roſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mary dryed, and Frankincenſe; of each a like quantity; make them into pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and ſtrow about half a ſpoonful hereof upon the Coales.</p>
               <p>Uſe alſo to burn in thy Chamber Juniper-wood; or for want thereof, Aſh-wood, and uſe to caſt on the fire Frankincenſe, Storax, Calamint. If one be infected with the Peſtilence, and a ſore begin to ariſe between the thigh and the privy Members, it is a ſign that
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:119681:83"/>
the Liver purgeth out the infection, in that place: then bleed on the Foot in the ſame ſide the ſwelling appears, the Vein betwixt thy great Toe; And if the botch be more outward to the ſide, and further from the privy Members, bleed then on the Vein between the Ankle and the Foot.</p>
               <p>If the matter appear in the cleanſing place of the Head, then conſider well in what ſide it appears, and bleed on the Medium Vein of the Arm, or the Vein of the Hand, between the Thumb and the next finger of the ſame ſide; but take good heed that you ſleep not in 12 hours after bleeding.</p>
               <p>It is good alwayes to have in your hand to ſmell to, this Pomander fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, which comforteth the Vital Spirits.</p>
               <p>Take Lapdanum purified an ounce, Storax Calamita diſſolved; Roſes, Cloves, Mace; of each three half penny weight, and make them into powder: add thereto 5 ſpoonfulls of Oil de Bay, an ounce of Virgins Wax: mingle them well all together, and make there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of a Ball of the quantity of a Wal-Nut.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="149" facs="tcp:119681:83"/>It is neceſſary in time of Peſtilence, or hot Agues, to waſh thy Temples, and the Pulſes of thy hands with Roſe-water, and Betony-water, And to wet linen Cloths therein, and lay to thy Temples, Fore-head, and Liver, and to each Arm-hole, one 4 times double.</p>
               <p>Let thy Cods be alwayes freſhly waſhed, and after dipt in Roſe-water; let thy Cap be dipt alſo in Roſe-water, after it is clean waſhed; and drye it in the fire, and not in the infected Air.</p>
               <p>Drink every morning 9 ſpoonfulls of white-Wine, in a ſawcer full of fine Vinegar; before thou go abroad out of thy houſe.</p>
               <p>You ſhall underſtand, that all the principal Members, the Heart, Brain, and Liver, have every one his proper purging place given him by nature; whereby he may avoyd all infections and ſuperfluities, and clear himſelf thereof.</p>
               <p>The Heart hath his cleanſing place in the Armpits.</p>
               <p>The Liver hath his cleanſing place in the groyn, between the Thigh and the Body.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="150" facs="tcp:119681:84"/>The clenſing place of the Brain is under the Ears, at the Ear-Roots, and in the Throat.</p>
               <p>Then the ſickneſs of the Peſtilence cometh thus: when the Pores of the Body are open, then firſt entreth the venemous and corrupt Air, which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecteth the blood; and then cometh to the Heart, that is the Root and ground of Life, and infecteth all the lively Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits in man; whereof death inſues: but the Heart and clean blood ſeeketh to expel, and fly from all that is noy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and contrary unto mankind. And the Heart ſeeketh to expel the Corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and venom from him to his clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing place the Arm-hole: But then ſomtimes that place is ſtopped, that it cannot come out; then it ſoon paſſeth to the next principal Member the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, And then the Liver doth in his kind endeavour to expel it by his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging place the Groyn: but if he be weak or obſtructed, that he cannot ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell it, then it runneth to the third principal Member the Brain, which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ſtriveth to expell, and drive it out by his purging place in the Throat, and under the Ears: but if through the
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:119681:84"/>
ſtopping of the Pores, or thickneſs of the Venemous matter that is mingled with the blood, it is hindred of this kindly courſe; then are all the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall Members infected and overcome thereby; whereupon death follows.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Againſt infection.</head>
               <p>In the morning alwayes before you go abroad, be ſure to break your faſt; and waſh your mouth with Vinegar, wherein Worm-wood hath been boyled; and afterwards hold in your mouth a bit of Zaedoary Root, Citron-Peels, Tormentil, Angelica or Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cornes-horn.</p>
               <p>Alſo it is good to anoynt the mouth, lips, and noſe, with this Compoſition following.</p>
               <p>Take the Juyce of Garlick, and Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar of Roſes; of each one ounce and a half, Treacle 3 quarters of an ounce, Beaver-Cod 2 dragmes: mix them to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether for an Oyntment.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="152" facs="tcp:119681:85"/>
               <head>Another Oyntment to anoynt the Heart, not only for thoſe that are well, but for thoſe that are already infected.</head>
               <p>Take 3 quarters of an ounce of Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, Saffron, and Canaphire; of each 10 grains, Juyce of Lemons, and Vinegar, as much as is needful to make a Salve thereof.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Pomander to ſmell to in Summer, for them that be of a hot Complexion.</head>
               <p>Take Water Lilley-flowers, Mynts, Violets, Vine-leaves, Roſes, Mittle-ſeeds, white and yellow Sanders, Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron-Peels, dryed Quinces, dryed Prunes; of each half a dragme, Saffron and Camphire; of each a ſcruple, Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia Muſcata 10 grains: make them up into a Pomander ball with Vinegar, wherein fine Bolus is diſſolved.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="153" facs="tcp:119681:85"/>
               <head>Another Pomander to be uſed in Plague-time.</head>
               <p>Take Roſes a quarter of an ounce, red and white Saunders; of each one dragme and a half, Camphire, Cinamon, Mace, and Nutmegs; of each one ſcruple, Amber, Citron-Peels, of each half a dragme, Musk 4 grains, red Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rax half an ounce, Laudanum 1 ounce: beat them ſmall, but diſſolve the Lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danum with Liquid Storax, and make thereof a Pomander.</p>
               <p>Care muſt be taken in times of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, to keep drye, and comfort the Heart, and principal Members; for which it is good to take once a week a dragme of Mithridate and Treacle in Sorrel-water, and ſweat after it: and keep within Doors all the day after.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Pills preſervative againſt the Plague.</head>
               <p>Take the Peſtilential Pills, called at the Apothecaries, Pill Ruffi 4 ſcruples, Agarick prepared half a dragm, Zedory, and Angelica, of each one dragm, Rha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barb 1 ſcruple, Trochiſci Alhaudal 5
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:119681:86"/>
grains: make Pills hereof with Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duns water, take a dragme hereof once a week 3 hours after Supper: in the morning drink a draught of the Deco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of Peaſe, and faſt 3 hours after it,</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Confection to ſtrengthen and preſerve nature againſt corrupt and Peſtilent Airs.</head>
               <p>Take Sealed Earth, white Diptamus: fine Bolus, Myrrhe, Wormwood, Rue, Scabious, Pimpernel, Sorrel, and Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doary, of each 1 dragme, Ariſtolochy, Tormentil, and Bay-leaves; of each 1 dragme and a half, 5 or 6 Kernels of Wal-nuts 12 new Figgs, Mithridate and Treacle, of each an ounce, Saffron and Camphire; of each one ſcruple, Unicorns-horn, prepared Pearls, Bones of a Stagges Heart, burnt Harts-horn and Smaragdes; of each one dragme and a half, Citron-ſeeds peeled half an ounce, Mace 1 dragme: pound all that is to be pounded, &amp; with Syrrup of Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons make them into a Confection; and take a little hereof morning and even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, in Winter, in a draught of Malm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſey or Muſcadine, and in Summer with Roſe-water.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="155" facs="tcp:119681:86"/>
               <head>A Powder againſt the Plague.</head>
               <p>Take Pimpernel, Gentian, Tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till, Dragon, Rue, Worm-wood, Nut Kernels, Granats prepared, and Juni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Berryes; of each a like quantity: uſe it upon a toſted piece of bread; or if you will, you may make a Confection hereof with Treacle, and Vinegar of Roſes.</p>
               <p>Thus far by way of prevention, if one be infected: The firſt means to be uſed, is to provoke ſweat, and that both morning and evening, (if the Patient can abide it,) for which you may uſe this Confection.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Confection to cauſe ſweat, when one is infected of the Plague.</head>
               <p>Take Treacle and Mithridate, of each half an ounce, Pimpernel, and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelica; of each 10 grains, Cardamom 5 grains, Camphire 5 grains, Cinamon 10 grains; make thereof a Confection; give the Patient the quantity of a Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zel-Nut thereof, in Carduus or Sorrel-water; and then cover him well, and let
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:119681:87"/>
him ſweat well 3 or 4 hours after, if he be able. If you have none of this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection ready at hand, then take a dragme of Treacle or Mithridate, in Carduus or Sorrel-water.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Diaphoretical Potion, that expelleth the Contagion of the Plague, and all Venom and Peſtilent Diſeaſes.</head>
               <p>Take Rue, Worm-wood, and the up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>permoſt tops of Black-berryes; of each a handful, Celendine a handful and a half; put them into a Pot with a pinte of Vinegar, and ſtop the Pot very cloſe, that there come in no air, nor no va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pour get out; and then let them ſeeth in <hi>Balneo,</hi> till the third part be conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med: then ſtrain it out, and keep it cloſe ſtopt; give the Patient 2 or 3 ounces of this drink when he is infected, and let him ſweat after it, and not ſleep.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>An Oil to provoke ſweat, and expel the Venome of the Plague.</head>
               <p>Take a glaſſe Bottle as big as you will, fill it halffull of Elder flowers, a third part of Holly-hock Flowers, and
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:119681:87"/>
uppermoſt a third part of the Flowers of St. Johns-wort; filling herewith the glaſſe: then put thereon old Sallad-Oil as much as the glaſſe will hold; ſtop it very cloſe, and let it ſtand a ſunning a whole Summer; with this Oil rub the Body very warm 3 or 4 times a day; it provoketh ſweat abundantly.</p>
               <p>Anoynt the ſick Perſons Breaſt or Heart, with this Medicine following.</p>
               <p>Take of the beſt Treacle one ounce, Juyce of Lemmons and Vinegar, of each half an ounce, Saffron and Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phire, of each one ſcruple: mingle them together, and ſpread them on a piece of Scarlet, and apply it: If a Plague-ſoar begin to appear with any redneſs, and will not impoſthumate, then take a young Pullet, &amp; pull off the feathers off her Belly; then cut her open and hold it upon the ſwelling: then ſhortly after take another, and do as before.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another to draw out the Plague-ſore.</head>
               <p>Take a great Onyon, and roaſt it with Treacle therein, and lay it upon the ſoar with a plaiſter of Oxicroceum, and Diachilon <hi>cum Gummis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="158" facs="tcp:119681:88"/>Alſo take the common Plaiſter of Diachilor 3 dragmes, and the Juyce of Celendine; and make a Salve thereof with a little Wax: or ſeeth Cole-worts with a little Bacon, and lay it on the ſwelling; and when you ſee it begin to impoſthumate, then uſe this following.</p>
               <p>Take Holly-hock Roots, Scabious, and Mallows; of each a like quantity: ſeeth them and beat them to a Pap, and make thereof a Plaiſter with Barrows-Greaſe; And apply it to the ſwelling.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To kill the Plague-ſoar.</head>
               <p>Take 2 or 3 yolks of new laid Egges, and temper therewith about half an ounce of Salt pounded ſmall, and lay it on the place, renewing it every quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of an hour.</p>
               <p>If the ſore Corrode further, take fine Bolus, Dragons-blood, Vinegar, Roſe-water, and whites of Egges, as much as you pleaſe: lay the ſame Plaiſter-wiſe upon the ſore.</p>
               <p>When the Plague-ſore is throughly killed, take Scabious 4 handfuls, Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle one ounce, Barrows-Greaſe one ounce and a half: ſtamp the Herbs, and
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:119681:88"/>
make a Plaiſter thereof, and refreſh it often.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To clenſe the Ulcer, and ingender new fleſh when other accidents are paſt.</head>
               <p>Take Turpentine, waſhed in Scabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous water 4 ounces, Barly-meal one ounce, two yolks of Egges, Saffron, Sar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cocolla, Maſtick and Frankincenſe; of each half a dragme: mix them all toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for a Plaiſter.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, take Beaten half an ounce, Honey of Roſes a ſufficient quantity, to make thereof a Salve; uſe it till the ſore be perfectly whole. <hi>Et Laudate Dominum.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>A fulgure &amp; tempestate, A Peſtilentia &amp; fame, a bello &amp; Caedibus, A ſubitanea, &amp; improviſa morte, Abira tua, &amp; a morte perpetua; libera nos Domine, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </q>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:119681:89"/>
            <pb n="161" facs="tcp:119681:89"/>
            <head>OF URINES.</head>
            <p>IN the Judgment of Urines, you muſt have regard to the Subſtance, Colours, Regions, and Contents. And theſe be the Colours of Waters that follow.</p>
            <p>Urine white as Clay-water of a Well, this Colour ſignifies ill Digeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, a bad Stomack, and a bad Liver: if you ſee in this Colour many ſhining beams, it denotes an Impoſthume in the Milt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Medicine.</hi> Take Gromel, Saxifrage, Parſly, and Sage; boyl them in ſtale Ale, and drink it: Alſo uſe powder of them in thy Pottage.</p>
            <p>If the Urine be white as Whey, thick, and little in quantity; it betokeneth the flux.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Medicine.</hi> Make Drink with white Poppy-Seeds, and Lettice, and uſe it.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="162" facs="tcp:119681:90"/>A white Ruſſet: if it be thick in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, it betokeneth the <hi>Cholica Paſſio.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Medicine.</hi> Take Water-Creſſes and grinde them ſmall, and boyl them in white-Wine, and drink thereof even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and morning.</p>
            <p>Urine of the Colour, as it were broth of fleſh half ſodden; If it be little in quantity, and fat as Oil, and frothy above, it betokeneth waſting.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Medicine.</hi> Take the powder of Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>campane and Turmentil; and boyl them with clarifyed Honey, and make a Confection thereof, and ſo uſe it.</p>
            <p>Urine of the Colour of broth of fleſh well ſodden, and thick in ſubſtance; it denotes a quotidian Fever that comes of Flegme. And this and all the other 5 colours are ſigns of bad Digeſtion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Medicine.</hi> Take Vinegar and Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtard, and boyl them together, and then take Treacle as much as a bean or two: waſh it with white-Wine, and mix therewith, and uſe it when the ſickneſs taketh thee.</p>
            <p>Urine of a yellow Colour, as a yellow Apple, with a thin ſubſtance, and a ſalt ſavour, betokeneth a double Tertian
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:119681:90"/>
that comes of Melancholy.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Medicine.</hi> Take Figges, Licorice, Hyſſop, Hore-hound and Elecampane: and boyl them in water till half be waſted, and drink thereof morning and night.</p>
            <p>Colour of Urine red as Saffron, if any yellow froth above it, betokens the Jaundice.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Medicine.</hi> Take Mirobalans, Aloes, Epatick, Sene, Sugar and Annis: make them into powder, and uſe thereof at night and morning.</p>
            <p>Urine as pale Gold, and thin in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, in a Child denotes a quotidian; in a young Man a tertian; in an old Man a double tertian; and in a Woman a quartain.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Medicine.</hi> Take Powder of <hi>Gete,</hi> the ſeed of Creſſes, and ſeeds of Broom; and uſe it in thy Pottage.</p>
            <p>Of the Colour of red Gold, thick in ſubſtance, and ſhaddowing above, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tokens a laſting quotidian.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Medicine.</hi> Take Satyrion-Roots, Muſtard-ſeed, Pepper, Annis and Cina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon: and mix them with Honey to an Electuary, and ſo uſe it.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="164" facs="tcp:119681:91"/>Urine as red as a Roſe, and thick, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>notes a burning Fever.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Medicine.</hi> Let him blood under the Ancle, or on the Vein of the Arm; And take Aloes, Epatick 1 dragme, and boyl it in a pinte of white-Wine, and drink thereof a ſpoonful, at evening and in the morning.</p>
            <p>Urine as black Wine, or rotten blood, This in a laſting Fever betoke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth death: if it be troubled, fatty and ſtinking, it betokens burſting of a Vein in the Reyns.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Medicine.</hi> Take Oſmond, Savin, and Gromel; and boyl them with white-Wine, and clarifyed Honey; and uſe it firſt and laſt.</p>
            <p>Urine green as worts, and little in quantity, betokens death.</p>
            <p>Urine black as a Coal, fatty and ſtinking, betokens death.</p>
            <p>Subrufus is like Gold &amp; Silver medly.</p>
            <p>This Colour betokens a Fever and Impoſthume. If there be a Circle with ſmall Bells in it, as it were of rain-wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, it is a wind in th Head that riſeth out of the Stomack.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Medicine.</hi> Take powder of Elecam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pane and Turmentil, and boyl them to
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:119681:91"/>
a Confection with Honey, and uſe it.</p>
            <p>Albus, like a cleer water, it denotes waſting of the Spleen, the Dropſie, Madneſs, piſſing againſt ones will, heat of the Liver, Emrods, and ſtopping of the Flowers,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Medicine.</hi> Make a Drink of Gromel, Saxifrage, Pellitory, Sage, and Hemp: &amp; ſeeth them in ſtale Ale, and drink it.</p>
            <p>When the Urine hath great contents and ſtink, it betokeneth pain in the Reyns and the Spleen.</p>
            <p>If it be bloudy and cleer, and pure, it denotes a Vein broke in the Liver; if it be little, with a ſtrong ſavour, and ly in Gobbets in the Bottome, it co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth from the bladder: If it be ſpotted as bloud, and red, the pain is in the Reyns and in the ſhare.</p>
            <p>If it be cleer and blackiſh, then the pain is in the back, and in the ſhare, and about the bladder.</p>
            <p>Raw humours is a content of the Urine; which you ſhall know thus.</p>
            <p>If the Urine after his caſting fleet full of Gravel motes, which come of the reſidence of the bottom, or in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle Region, then in the Urine be raw humours; And if the raw humours be
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:119681:92"/>
above on the water, it betokeneth a ſtraitneſs in the Breaſt, and ſhortneſs of breath, and nipping of the Spleen: If it appear in the middle, it ſignifies griping in the Body and Guts, and wind in the Stomack, which cometh of exceſſe of meat and drink. And if they be in the bottome, the pain is in the Reyns, and ſometimes it is in the Cod.</p>
            <p>Fat without Axys, betokeneth wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting of Greaſe about the Fundament: if it be with Axys, waſting of the Body.</p>
            <p>Moates white, ſmall and round, ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies the Gout both in Man and Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man.</p>
            <p>Spermatick Reſolutions, if they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear fleeting about in the Urine, and the Urine raw in Colour; it denotes involuntary waſting of the Seed.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>How to know Mans Urine from Womans, and Beaſts from Man or Woman.</head>
               <p>You ſhall underſtand, that if there be any trouble in Mans Urine, it ſheweth it ſelf in the midſt of the Urine: and in the Womans Urine it doth not ſo. And the froth after the caſting of Mans Urine, it ſhall be long;
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:119681:92"/>
and of a Womans after the caſting it ſhall be round: thus ſaith <hi>Avicenna.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now to know Beaſts Water from Mans Water; Beaſts Water is more ſad and ſubtil of Complexion. Alſo the Beaſts Water ſwelleth more then the Mans.</p>
               <p>Alſo mingle the Urine of a Beaſt with a Mans, and they ſhall part aſunder.</p>
               <p>And if it be a Cow that is with Calf, the Contents of the Cows Urine is much greater then the Urine of a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man; in as much as the Woman is leſſe (and fair of Complexion) then the Cow is.</p>
               <p>Urine fat and troubled, betokeneth a burning Fever that cometh of Choler.</p>
               <p>Urine red and thick over all with a black Circle, betokens ſickneſs over all: and if the Patient ſweat not, it is death.</p>
               <p>Urine white and thin, and little, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares cold in the Body.</p>
               <p>Urine cleer with a black Circle, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tokeneth the Tiſſick.</p>
               <p>Urine thin and ſomwhat black above in the caſting, declares great loſſe of Nature.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="168" facs="tcp:119681:93"/>Urine thick and troubled as Horſe-piſſe, betokens Head-ach.</p>
               <p>Urine fat in the bottome, white in the midſt, and red above, betokens a Fever quartain.</p>
               <p>Urine that hath black Contents, ſmall as moats in the midſt of the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, ſignifies an Impoſthume under the ſide.</p>
               <p>Urine that hath grains under the Circle, betokens a Stomack full of Worms, and burning of the Heart.</p>
               <p>Urine that is foul above, ſignifies heat in the Heart, in the Lungs, and in the Spleen.</p>
               <p>Urine frothy, cleer, and a little red, betokens pain under the right ſide.</p>
               <p>Urine of a Woman that is with Child, that Water ſhal have ſome cleer ſtrikes: and the moſt part ſhall be troubled; and the troubleneſs ſhall be reddiſh in the manner of a tawney: and this token ſhall never fail. As ſoon as the Child hath life, if it be a Girle, the trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs ſhall draw downward; and if it be a Boy, it ſhall aſcend above.</p>
               <p>Urine of a Woman, white, heavy and ſtinking, betokeneth pain in the Reyns, and pain of the Mother, and ſickneſs of cold.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="169" facs="tcp:119681:93"/>Urine of a Woman ſhining as bright Gold, ſignifyeth luſt to a man.</p>
               <p>Urine of a Woman that fleeteth fat above, betokens pain in the Reyns.</p>
               <p>Urine of a Woman with black Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents in the bottome, betokens falling of the Flowers.</p>
               <p>Urine of a Woman coloured as white Lead; if ſhee be with Child, the Child is dead within her. And if ſhee be not with Child, and the Water ſtink, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tokeneth that the Mother is rotten.</p>
               <p>Urine of a Woman coloured as Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeed, and if ſhee have the flux, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tokeneth death.</p>
               <p>Urine of a Woman red as Gold, with a watry Circle above, ſignifies that ſhe is with Child.</p>
               <p>If thou ſee thy face in a Womans Water, and ſhee be without a Fever, it betokeneth ſhee is with Child. But if thou ſee thy face in the Urine of a hot Fever, it is a ſign of death.</p>
               <p>And if thou ſee thy face in Urine that hath no Axes, it betokens long ſickneſs.</p>
               <p>Urine thin in ſubſtance, having fleet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing above as it were a dark Skye, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tokens death.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="170" facs="tcp:119681:94"/>
               <head>Of the Regions of the Urine.</head>
               <p>You ſhall underſtand, that in the Urine, when it is in the Urinal, there be three Regions. The firſt, ſecond, and the third.</p>
               <p>The third beginneth at the bottome of the Urinal, and laſteth to the thick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of a fingers bredth upward.</p>
               <p>The ſecond Region begins as the 3 doth end, and laſteth upward to the Circle.</p>
               <p>And the firſt Region contains all that is upward above the Circle. And in theſe Regions be divers Contents.</p>
               <p>There be 4 Contents that belong to Urines, which I will here declare to you; and firſt, I will begin at froth. Froth that dwelleth and cleaveth to the Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, betokeneth indigeſtion, and wind in the Stomack, and in the Bowells, and in the Head: And if above that froth dwell great Bubbles, it betokeneth great pain in the Reyns.</p>
               <p>And if the froth dwell ſmall, it's a ſign of burning in the Stomack, and burnt bloud in the Liver.</p>
               <p>If the froth be full of grains, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tokens
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:119681:94"/>
Rheume in the Head, Breaſt, and the black Jaundice.</p>
               <p>If it be green, it's a ſign of the Jaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice that cometh of burnt bloud in the Liver.</p>
               <p>A ſmall skye appearing and ſhadow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Urine above; if the Urine be a party blew, it betokeneth pain at the Heart, and ſhortneſs of breath, and wind that cometh of the Lungs: And if the Urine be not blew, and ſuch a skye ſhadow the Urine above it, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tokens chafing of the Liver, and eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally if the froth be yellow.</p>
               <p>A Circle thick, and little Colour, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tokeneth pain in the Brains.</p>
               <p>A Circle thick and little, and colou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red as Purple, betokeneth pain in the forehead.</p>
               <p>A Circle black or white, thin, and a little coloured, betokens pain in the left ſide of the Head.</p>
               <p>A Circle thin and high-coloured, as red or yellow, ſignifies pain in the right ſide of the Head.</p>
               <p>A Circle green, betokens wavering in the Head, and pain in the Stomack; And if it appear in an hot Axis, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tokeneth the phrenſy that cometh of cold.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="172" facs="tcp:119681:95"/>A Circle in a hot Axis, coloured blew, if it trembled, betokeneth death.</p>
               <p>Grains that dwell in the Circle, after caſting of the Urine gone down, and after riſe up again to the Circle, they betoken Rheume in the Head.</p>
               <p>And if they go down, and turn not again to the Circle, then they ſignify Rheume in the Breaſt, Lungs, and the Spleen: And if you ſee 2 ſmall grains, or more, in the ſecond Region, knit to a ſmall skye, they betoken pain in the Breaſt, of Rheume, a bad Stomack, Liver and Lungs.</p>
               <p>Urine white or pale, neither too thick nor too thin, with an even and clean ſubſtance, betokeneth health in a Melancholy man.</p>
               <p>Urine white as Water, and not thin, with beams as they were yards, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing in the midſt, betokens ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Spleen.</p>
               <p>Theſe be the tokens: overthwart ſwelling in the ſide, with hardneſs, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digeſtion, a ſmall Neck, a lean Body, heavineſs and ſloath in all the Body, Eſpecially if they go againſt a Hill; Paleneſs of Viſage, and ſwelling after meat.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="173" facs="tcp:119681:95"/>Urine white and thin, with fleſhly and long reſolutions, much in quantity, and often made, betokens a ſickneſs that is called Diabites; and of the ſaid ſickneſs, cometh Urine overmuch and unmeaſurably. The tokens are, great thirſt, unmeaſurable dryneſs of Body; and this breedeth often the Dropſie.</p>
               <p>Urine white and thin, with ſmall round moats, betokeneth the cold Gout.</p>
               <p>The tokens are. The Patient is wan of colour, and ſhaking.</p>
               <p>Urine white and thin as Water, with a manner of darkeneſs, and with Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel, betokeneth the ſtone, and the ſpices thereof; as is ſhewed in the Contents.</p>
               <p>Urine white and thin, long conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuing, with Scales, and black reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſignifies in Womans Water, ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of her Flowers. The tokens are, ach in the Head, and Back, and Neck, and in the nether part of the Body, And an evill appetite to meat.</p>
               <p>Urine in the beginning red, and ſhining as flames of fire, and thin, and after white and thin; betokeneth the Phrenſie.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="174" facs="tcp:119681:96"/>Theſe be the tokens: a Fever, Ague, great thirſt, Alienation of minde, and many times they think their bed is full of ſtraw, or ſuch like things, which they ſeek after; and when they cannot find it, they be very raging.</p>
               <p>Urine white and thin as colour of Lead with whiteneſs, betokens the fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ſickneſs.</p>
               <p>Theſe be the tokens: heavineſs of the Head, ſloath of the Body, Yawning, Quaking of the Hands and Feet, Pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of Nature, piſſing involuntarily.</p>
               <p>Urine white and thin, and cleer, and much ſhining, and little Gravel appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, betokens the ſwimming in the Head, which is called Vertigo.</p>
               <p>Theſe be the tokens: ach in the Head, and eſpecially in the forehead, dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Eyes, and overcaſting of the uppermoſt part: ſo that if they ſee wheels go, or running water, they fall down; loathings of meat, and often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times abomination of the Stomach.</p>
               <p>Urine white and thin in lean people, betokeneth waſting of the ſubſtance of the Body.</p>
               <p>Theſe be the tokens: the Face is wan, the Eyes hollow and drye, a faint
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:119681:96"/>
heat like a ſoft Fever, in the hands, loathing of meat.</p>
               <p>Urine white and thin, in what ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs ſoever it be, betokeneth indigeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and feebleneſs of natural heat.</p>
               <p>The tokens be theſe: cloſing of wind under the Ribs and the Sides, rumbling in the womb, ſwelling of the Sides, heavineſs of the Eyes and Joynts; The Body ſlothful, and evil diſpoſed on the left ſide. And thus have I ſet before you the Symptomes of Diſeaſes our frail Bodyes are incident unto, mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted by the Urine: if you deſire to know the Medicines, look into the Table annexed to this Mirror of Health, where you will find ſeveral fitted, and plainly prepared for you; for which means give God the praiſe.</p>
            </div>
            <closer>
               <hi>Triuni Deo, ſacro-Sanctae &amp; individuae Trinitati, ſit Honor &amp; Gloria, in ſecula ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culorum,</hi> Amen.</closer>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>23 July 1656. <hi>Sol</hi> in <hi>Aries</hi> 10. 33.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Per</hi> Rob. Turner.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
